<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>103</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Amidopyrylium-Fluoreszenz-Farbstoffe</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Norbert Uwe</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Kemnitzer</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Fluoreszenzfarbstoffe</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Fluoreszenzsonden</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Roter Spektralbereich</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">540</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Fluoreszenzbasierte Untersuchungsmethoden gewinnen aufgrund ihrer hohen&#13;
Nachweisempfindlichkeit speziell in der biochemischen Analytik und medizinischen&#13;
Diagnostik zunehmend an Bedeutung. Häufig werden dabei fluoreszierende Farbstoffe als so&#13;
genannte Fluoreszenzsonden zur Markierung von Biomolekülen eingesetzt. Vor allem der rote&#13;
Spektralbereich bietet eine Reihe von Vorteilen, so dass es sinnvoll ist, Farbstoffe zu&#13;
verwenden, die oberhalb von 600 nm absorbieren und fluoreszieren.&#13;
Bisher gibt es nur wenige Klassen intensiv rot fluoreszierender Farbstoffe, wie z. B. Cyanine,&#13;
Oxazine, Carbopyronine und einige Xanthenderivate. 1971 wurde die erste Synthese einer&#13;
neuen Klasse langwellig absorbierender Farbstoffe beschrieben. Diese amidüberbrückten&#13;
Benzopyryliumfarbstoffe sind Gegenstand der vorliegenden Arbeit. Es wurde eine große&#13;
Anzahl neuer Vertreter dieser Farbstoffklasse dargestellt und ihre spektralen Eigenschaften&#13;
untersucht. Neben der Strukturabhängigkeit der Absorptionswellenlänge wird die&#13;
Beeinflussung des Absorptions- und Fluoreszenzverhaltens durch Lösungsmittelumgebung,&#13;
pH-Wert und Temperatur vorgestellt.&#13;
Die Amidopyryliumfarbstoffe absorbieren zwischen 590 und 680 nm und zeigen eine&#13;
besonders große Stokes-Verschiebung von zirka 50 nm. Aus experimentellen Daten kann die&#13;
natürliche Lebensdauer der Amidopyryliumfarbstoffe zu 8 ns abgeschätzt werden. Bei&#13;
Raumtemperatur variiert die Fluoreszenzquantenausbeute der Farbstoffe in Abhängigkeit von&#13;
der Molekülstruktur zwischen 10 und 50 %. Auch die Lösungsmittelumgebung sowie&#13;
Viskosität und Temperatur haben einen starken Einfluss auf die Quantenausbeute.&#13;
Eine Verbesserung der Stabilität der Farbstoffe in basischem Medium konnte durch die&#13;
Einführung eines Carboxyphenylsubstituenten erreicht werden, da die Entstehung einer&#13;
farblosen Pseudobase verhindert wird. Es wurden außerdem Amidopyryliumfarbstoffe mit&#13;
koppelbaren Carboxylgruppen dargestellt, die als Fluoreszenzsonde eingesetzt werden&#13;
können.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">The measurement of fluorescence has become a very useful tool in medical and biological&#13;
diagnostics as well as in environmental analysis and material sciences due to the high&#13;
sensitivity of fluorescence spectroscopy. Many techniques and analytical concepts use&#13;
fluorescent dyes for labelling of biological compounds. It is possible to enhance the&#13;
sensitivity of detection by using marker dyes that absorb and fluoresce in the red or near&#13;
infrared spectral region.&#13;
Only few dyes exhibiting intense red fluorescence have been known until recently, e. g.&#13;
cyanines, oxazines, carbopyronins and some xanthene derivatives. A new class of fluorescent&#13;
dyes for the red region of the visible spectrum is the topic of this thesis. The first synthesis of&#13;
the amide-bridged benzopyrylium dyes was published in 1971. A great variety of new dyes&#13;
belonging to this class of fluorescent dyes has been prepared. Their spectral properties, i. e.&#13;
absorption and fluorescence, have been studied with emphasis on temperature and&#13;
environmental (solvent, pH) influences.&#13;
The absorption maximum of the amidopyrylium dyes occurs, depending on the molecular&#13;
structure, in the region between 590 and 680 nm. A special feature of these dyes is the large&#13;
Stokes shift of about 50 nm. From experimental data a natural fluorescence lifetime of about&#13;
8 ns can be expected. The quantum yield of fluorescence of the dyes varies, depending on the&#13;
molecular structure, between 10 and 50 % at room temperature. The solvent, viscosity and&#13;
temperature have a strong influence on the quantum yield.&#13;
Amidopyrylium dyes can form a colourless pseudobase in alkaline media. It is possible to&#13;
protect the reactive centre by a spacious carboxyphenyl substituent. Such dyes are stable&#13;
towards base. Further it was possible to introduce coupling groups, e. g. COOH, without&#13;
affecting the optical properties of the dyes. Via an active ester such dyes can be coupled easily&#13;
to amino groups of proteins, nucleotides and other analyte molecules and thus can be used as&#13;
long-wavelength fluorescent labels.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2001-07-13</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2001</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-1038</dc:identifier>
   <dc:source xsi:type="ddb:noScheme">Osnabrück : Der Andere Verl., 2001</dc:source>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">ger</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fachbereich 8, Chemie - Biologie</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="kemnitzer.pdf" ddb:fileSize="2782578"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">4db5ff2821a66b32d7070887a7f68c99</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/103/1/kemnitzer.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/103</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>