<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>1035</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Protected STED and multicolour multilevel STED nanoscopy</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Sven-Christian</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Sidenstein</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">STED-Mikroskopie</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Hochauflösende Mikroskopie</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Fluoreszenzmikroskopie</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">STED</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Neuron</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Superresolution Microscopy</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Nanoscopy</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Fluorescence Microscopy</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">STED</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">540</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">The diffraction barrier of focused light has been overcome by modern superresolution fluorescence microscopy techniques. These methods harness transitions between signaling and non-signaling states of the marker molecules to make them discernible at length scales of few tens of nanometers. Although superresolution methods like STED (STimulated Emission Depletion) and RESOLFT (REversible Saturable Optical Linear Fluorescence Transitions) microscopy proved to be valuable tools for cell biology, neurobiology and other fields, further improvements are needed. For example, lower fluorophore bleaching rates and enhanced state contrasts of the molecule ensemble are desired. Moreover, biological studies ask for better multicolour schemes allowing simultaneous imaging of multiple cellular structures with nanoscopic resolution. In this thesis, novel methods for coordinate-targeted superresolution microscopy are presented, which take up these challenges. Superresolution imaging with Multiple Off-State Transitions (MOST) is introduced and realized by reversible photoswitching and STED of fluorescent proteins leading to a new method called ´protected STED´. On the basis of measurements in different biological samples, it can be shown that in protected STED both fluorophore bleaching is reduced and state contrast is enhanced compared to conventional coordinate-targeted superresolution methods. Also, in this theses, a novel multicolour scheme is presented, which is based on a STED wavelength of 620 nm and which is valuable for imaging of both fixed and living samples. Furthermore, with multilevel STED, a new method was developed, which in multicolour imaging with a single STED beam improves both the image quality and avoids unnecessary STED light doses. Three-colour superresolution imaging harnessing multilevel STED was utilized to study nanoscale protein distributions in mature neurons. Periodic actin/βII spectrin lattices were found to be present along dendrites and thick spine necks, but they are absent from pre- and post-synaptic sites. These findings add new pieces to the picture of the nanoscale cytoskeletal arrangement in neurites.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Die Beugungsgrenze fokussierten Lichtes wurde durch moderne hochauflosende Fluoreszenzmikroskopieverfahren überwunden. Diese Methoden nutzen die (ir-)reversiblen Übergänge in leuchtende und nicht-leuchtende Zustände der Markermoleküle aus, um sie auf der Längenskala von wenigen zehn Nanometern unterscheidbar zu machen. Obwohl Methoden wie STED- (STimulierte Emissions-Depletions) und RESOLFT- (reversibel sättigbare optische Fluoreszenzübergänge, englisch REversible Saturable Optical Linear Fluorescence Transitions) Mikroskopie bereits gezeigt haben, dass sie wichtige Werkzeuge für die Zellbiologie, Neurobiologie und andere Forschungsgebiete sein konnen, sind weitere Verbesserungen notig. Dies betrifft zum Beispiel das Ausbleichen von Farbstoffmolekülen und den erreichbaren Zustandskontrast innerhalb des Molekülensembles. Des Weiteren werden für biologische Studien weiter verbesserte Mehrfarbenschemata benotigt, um gleichzeitig mehrere zelluläre Strukturen mit nanoskopischer Auflosung abbilden zu konnen. In dieser Arbeit werden neue Methoden für die Bewältigung dieser Herausforderungen vorgestellt. Zum einen wird die hochauflosende Mikroskopie mit mehreren Ausschaltübergängen (englisch Multiple Off-Switching Transitions, MOST) als neues Konzept eingeführt. Es wurde in der Form von ”protected STED“ realisiert, indem reversibles Fotoschalten und STED fluoreszierender Proteine kombiniert wurden. Anhand von Messungen in diversen biologischen Proben kann gezeigt werden, dass in ”protected STED“ sowohl das Farbstoffbleichen reduziert als auch der Zustandskontrast erhoht sind. Zum anderen wird ein Mehrfahrbenschema zur STED-Mikroskopie fixierter und lebender Proben präsentiert, das mit einer neuartigen STED-Wellenlänge von 620 nm realisiert wurde. Mit ”multilevel STED“ wird außerdem eine Methode eingeführt, die in Mehrfarbenaufnahmen mit einem einzelnen STED-Strahl sowohl die Bildqualität verbessert als auch unnotige STED-Lichtbeaufschlagung vermeidet. Das neue Schema und ”multilevel STED“ wurden genutzt, um Dreifarben-Hochauflosungsbilder der nanoskaligen Proteinverteilung in vollentwickelten Neuronen aufzunehmen. Ein periodisches Aktin/βII-Spektrin-Gitter konnte entlang von Dendriten und in großeren dendritischen Dornen nachgewiesen werden. In Prä- und Postsynapsen bleibt es jedoch aus. Damit konnten weitere Puzzlestücke zum Bild der nanoskaligen Zytoskelettstruktur in Neuronen hinzugefügt werden.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2016-08-11</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2016</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-10354</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät IV - Naturwissenschaftlich-Technische Fakultät</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Dissertation_Sven_Christian_Sidenstein.pdf" ddb:fileSize="31097068"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">2defbdbb440ed552a4c225360b6b6d0f</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/1035/1/Dissertation_Sven_Christian_Sidenstein.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/1035</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>