<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>1279</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Direct detection of electrons with the pnCCD for applications in transmission electron microscopy</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Direkte Detektion von Elektronen mit dem pnCCD für Anwendungen in der Transmissionselektronenmikroskopie</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Henning</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Ryll</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Halbleiterdetektor</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Signalantwort</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">pnCCD</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Electron</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Detection</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Electron-Microscope</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">530</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">In this dissertation, the signal response of the pnCCD under electron illumination was studied comprehensively. The pnCCD is a spatially resolving, fast, energy dispersive, charge-coupled-device (CCD) semiconductor detector that has great potential for applications in transmission electron microscopes (TEMs) as deduced from previous measurements with (X-ray) photons. However, there had not been an elaborate analysis of the pnCCD under electron illumination. The present work closes this gap with a detailed physical explanation and modelling of the signal response of the pnCCD to electrons established on a systematic investigation with experiments, simulations and analysis. A series of conducted, application-oriented experiments showed that the pnCCD improves analysis and methods in electron microscopy.&#13;
&#13;
As part of this work, a camera with the pnCCD was developed and mounted at TEMs at numerous research institutes. In a diversity of experiments, single TEM electrons were imaged in the energy range of 20keV to 300keV . From this data, energy spectra of single electrons were determined. With the analysis of these spectra in combination with simulations, the scattering of the TEM electrons inside the detector could be explained as well as the readout signals. A relevant influence on the measured signal is exerted by the backscattered electrons that do not deposit their full energy in the detector, but rather scatter out of it. On the basis of the developed analysis, the precise number of incoming TEM electrons can now be determined.&#13;
&#13;
The relationships between the readout signals, the pnCCD’s parameters and the parameters of the TEM (mainly the energy of the TEM electrons) were determined and explained. Furthermore, the spatial resolution was investigated. The spatial resolution could be increased with several models allowing images created with single TEM electrons to offer pixel sizes smaller than the given physical sizes. For TEM electron energies of</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">In dieser Dissertation wurde die Signalantwort des pnCCDs unter Bestrahlung mit Elektronen umfassend untersucht. Der pnCCD ist ein ortsauflösender, schneller und energiedispersiver »charged coupled device« (CCD)-Halbleiterdetektor, welchem abgeleitet von vorausgegangenen Messungen mit (Röntgen-) Photonen auch ein enormes Potenzial für Anwendungen in Transmissionselektronenmikroskopen (TEM) zugesprochen wurde. Es hatte jedoch bisher keine ausführliche Analyse des pnCCDs unter Beleuchtung mit Elektronen gegeben. Die vorliegende Arbeit füllt diese Lücke mit einer detaillierten physikalischen Beschreibung und Modellierung der Signalantwort des pnCCDs auf Elektronen, aufbauend auf einer systematischen Untersuchung durch Experimente, Simulationen und Analysen. In einer Reihe von anwendungsorientierten Experimenten wurde gezeigt, dass mit dem pnCCD Analysen und Methoden in der Elektronenmikroskopie grundlegend verbessert werden.&#13;
&#13;
Im Rahmen dieser Arbeit wurde eine Kamera mit dem pnCCD als bildgebenden Sensor entwickelt und an TEMs mehrerer Forschungsinstitute installiert. In verschiedenen Experimenten wurden unter anderem einzelne Elektronen im Bereich von 20keV bis 300keV abgebildet. Anhand dieser Aufnahmen konnten Energiespektren von einzelnen TEM Elektronen gewonnen werden. Durch die Analyse der Spektren konnten in Kombination mit Simulationen die Streuvorgänge in dem pnCCD untersucht und die ausgelesenen Signale erklärt werden. Einen signifikanten Einfluss haben hierbei TEM Elektronen, die nicht ihre gesamte Energie im Detektor deponieren, sondern wieder aus dem sensitiven Detektorvolumen heraus streuen. Die in diesem Zusammenhang entwickelten Analysen ermöglichen nun die präzise Anzahl der eintreffenden TEM Elektronen zu bestimmen.&#13;
&#13;
Die Abhängigkeiten zwischen den ausgelesenen Signalen, den pnCCD Parametern und den TEM Parametern (hauptsächlich die Energie der TEM Elektronen) wurden bestimmt und beschrieben. Weiterhin wurde das räumliche Auflösungsvermögen untersucht welches für die Abbildung von Einzelelektronen mit mehreren Modellen signifikant gesteigert werden konnte, so dass die Pixelgrößen in resultierenden Bildern kleiner sind als die gegebene physikalische Pixelgröße. Besonders für Elektronenenergien von</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2017-12-18</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2017</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-12795</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät IV - Naturwissenschaftlich-Technische Fakultät</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Dissertation_Henning_Ryll.pdf" ddb:fileSize="27424575"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">ce9232cd85655ee210cd5a92d24aca3c</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/1279/1/Dissertation_Henning_Ryll.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/1279</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>