<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>1309</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Experimental investigations on the dynamic behavior and fracture of composite materials</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Mohammad Reza</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Khosravani</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Schichtverbundwerkstoff</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Dynamic behaviour</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Sandwich composite</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Ultra-high performance concrete</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Split-Hopkinson bar, Dynamic material properties, FEM</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">620</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">Various types of composites are known to have excellent and superior mechanical properties. The extremely high strength to weight ratio and the high resistance to corrosion as favorable mechanical properties, converts the composites to multifunctional structures in various applications. This thesis focuses on details of experimental investigations of fracture mechanics on two different composite materials: a sandwich composite T-joint and an ultra-high performance concrete (UHPC).&#13;
The utilization of sandwich composites in aviation industry is significantly increased. In this respect, the aim of the current research is to identify the damage mechanism of sandwich composite T-joints and to obtain accurate material behavior under various loading and environmental conditions. For investigation of the sandwich composite Tjoints, series of experimental tests have been carried out in quasi-static and dynamic loading conditions and failure mechanisms are investigated. Moreover, effects of working conditions during the flight on the behavior of the sandwich composite are studied. To this end, the natural environment is simulated experimentally which influences the strength of the T-joints. This effect is determined by accelerated ageing of the honeycomb&#13;
sandwich T-joints.&#13;
Developments of material science as one pillar of modern technology, leads to substitute metallic materials with cementitious composites which can be counted a milestone in human living standards. Although a huge potential in application of UHPC material is given, technical information about the dynamic behavior of this material is still limited. In this dissertation, in order to study the UHPC response to the dynamic loading, series of spalling tests and dynamic Brazilian experiments have been conducted. In this regard, a linear elastic fracture mechanics-based approach is used to study the dynamic fracture and determine material properties under a high rate of loading. Parallel to the experiments, the performed tests on both mentioned composites, are numerically simulated in commercial finite element software.&#13;
By the obtained results from experiments on the sandwich composite T-joints, reliable technical information about the fracture behavior of this type of joint is provided. The achieved results prepare not only new data for the designers, but can also be used for future computational models of adhesively bonded composite T-joints. The outcomes of the experiments at high rate of loading on UHPC material, presents data regarding to response of this material to dynamic loading regime. The data extracted from the experiments can speed up the robust design and it is beneficial for future material developments and load carrying capabilities of this cementitious composite materials.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Viele Arten von Kompositen zeichnen sich durch hervorragende mechanische Eigenschaften aus. Das extrem hohe Verhältnis von Härte zu Gewicht und die Resistenz gegenüber Korrosion sind bevorzugte mechanische Eigenschaften, welche im Werkstoffverbund zu multifunktionalem Verhalten beitrangen und zu einer Vielzahl an Anwendungsmöglichkeiten führen. In der vorliegenden Arbeit wurde der Schwerpunkt auf experimentelle Untersuchungen und die Anwendung der Theorie der Bruchmechanik auf zwei verschiedene Werkstoffverbunde gelegt: zusammengesetzte Sandwich T-Stücke und ultrahochfester Beton (UHFB).&#13;
In der Luftfahrtindustrie hat die Verarbeitung von Sandwich-Werkstoffen erheblich zugenommen. Zielsetzungen dieser Forschungsarbeit sind die Identifikation des Schädigungsmechanismus von Sandwich T-Stücken und das Spezifizieren des präzisen Materialverhaltens unter verschiedenen Belastungen und Umgebungseinflüssen. Eine Serie von Untersuchungen der T-Stücke ist im quasistatischen und dynamischen Belastungsfall erfolgt- gekoppelt an verschiedene Modelle der Bruchmechanik. Zusätzlich wird der natürliche Umgebungseinfluss, wie er während des Fluges auf das Werkstück wirkt, untersucht. Hierzu wird der Werkstoffverbund künstlich und somit beschleunigt gealtert, um die Auswirkungen auf die Festigkeit beurteilen zu können.&#13;
Die Entwicklung der Materialwissenschaften als ein Träger moderner Technologie&#13;
führt zum Austausch der Metalle mit Zement-basierten Verbundwerkstoffen, welche als Meilenstein zur Verbesserung des Lebensstandards beitragen. Obwohl ein hohes Potential in der Anwendung von UHFB gesehen wird, sind die technischen Informationen über das dynamische Verhalten limitiert. Hier werden eine Reihe von Spaltungsversuchen und sogenannte Brazilian-Tests durchgeführt, sodass eine Aussage über das Verhalten von UHFB im dynamischen Fall getroffen werden kann. Die Untersuchung des dynamischen Bruchs und die Bestimmung der Materialeigenschaften unter hohen Belastungen basieren auf dem Ansatz eines linear-elastischen Materialverhaltens. Die durchgeführten Experimente, angewandt auf die beiden oben genannten Werkstoffe, werden mit einer kommerziellen Finiten-Elemente Software simuliert. &#13;
Die resultierenden experimentellen Werte für das T-Stück und technische Informationen ermöglichen eine Bewertung des Bruchverhaltens für diese Klasse von Verbindungen. Die in dieser Arbeit erzielten Ergebnisse liefern nicht nur neue Informationen für die Entewicklung der Werkstoffverbunde, sondern Bilden ebenfalls eine Grundlage für zukünftige Rechenmodelle hinsichtlich der genannten T-Stücke. Es wurde festgestellt, dass das Experiment bei hohen Belastungsraten zuverlässige Werte liefert. Die Errungenschaften sind von großer Bedeutung für die lasttragenden Möglichkeiten des auf Zement basierten Materials.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2018-04-23</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2018</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-13096</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Institut für Mechanik und Regelungstechnik - Mechatronik</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Dissertation_Mohammad_Reza_Khosravani.pdf" ddb:fileSize="17219495"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">53bbffd6bfaa5c9f39da3e9e8d29608e</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/1309/1/Dissertation_Mohammad_Reza_Khosravani.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/1309</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>