<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>1321</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">puppen in bedrohungsszenarien</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" ddb:type="translated" lang="eng">dolls/puppets in threat scenarios</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Insa</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Fooken</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Jana</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Mikota</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Franziska</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Burger</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Magali</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Nieradka-Steiner</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Julia von</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Dall’Armi</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Susanne</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Blumesberger</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Brooke</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Shafar</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Nils C.</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Ritter</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Jana</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Scholz</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Anna</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Friesen</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Natascha</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Compes</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Juliane</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Noack Napoles</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Gudrun</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Gauda</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Lin</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Cheng</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Robin</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Lohmann</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Gudrun</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Schulz</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Alexander</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Wagner</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Uta</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Brandes</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Hans-Wolfgang</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Nickel</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Puppe</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Puppennarrative</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Bedrohungsszenarien</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Übergangsobjekte</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">anthropomorphe Figuren</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Puppets</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Transition</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Anthropomorphism</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Threat scenarios</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">800</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Puppen in Bedrohungsszenarien – so lautet der Themenschwerpunkt der ersten Ausgabe der interdisziplinären online-Zeitschrift "denkste: puppe / just a bit of: doll" zu Mensch-Puppen-Diskursen (Akronym: de:do). Die Bezeichnung ‚Puppe’ steht dabei für anthropomorphe ,Wesen’ und Artefakte in all ihren unterschiedlichen Erscheinungsformen und der Begriff der Bedrohung wird hier weit gefasst. Ausgangspunkt der Entscheidung für diesen Fokus war die Annahme, dass Puppen und puppenaffinen Artefakten sowohl in Zeiten existenzieller Bedrohung als auch in Phasen innerpsychischer Beunruhigung und Irritation eine besondere Bedeutung zukommt. Die hier einbezogenen Beiträge stammen aus unterschiedlichen Fachdisziplinen und eröffnen in der bewusst nicht disziplinär ausgerichteten Zusammenstellung reizvolle multiperspektivische Mensch-Puppen-Diskurse. Dabei sind nicht nur die hier angesprochenen Themenbezüge, sondern auch die jeweiligen methodischen Zugänge ausgesprochen heterogen. So werden Puppen-Narrative aufgegriffen, die beispielsweise innerhalb der Literaturwissenschaft an die lange Tradition von Puppen-Erzählungen anknüpfen, aber auch solche, die aktuell in den Diskursen über Zukunftsszenarien und neue Technologien mittels verschiedener medialer Formate und/oder künstlerischer Aktionen für Diskussionsstoff sorgen.&#13;
Ein erster thematischer Fokus liegt auf der Bedeutung von Puppen im Zuge der Erfahrung von Bedrohung und Verlusten im Kontext von Krieg, Flucht und Verfolgung in politisch unsicheren Zeiten. Hier werden aus verschiedenen fachdisziplinären Perspektiven unterschiedliche Facetten von Bedrohungsszenarien angesprochen. So geht es aus theaterwissenschaftlicher Sicht um zwei Inszenierungen aus dem Bereich des Objekt- und Materialtheaters, in denen bedrohliche Kriegsdarstellungen mittels Plastikpuppen bzw. amorphen Materials aufbereitet werden. Aus psychologischer Perspektive kommen Rollen und Funktionen von Puppen als Übergangsobjekte im Kontext von Umbrüchen, Krieg und Gewalt zur Sprache. In zwei literaturwissenschaftlichen Beiträgen wird jeweils ein Roman aus der Kinder- und Jugendliteratur analysiert, in denen in einem Fall eine Puppe zur psychischen Stabilisierung der literarischen Protagonistin beiträgt und im anderen Fall das Schicksal der Puppe die Geschichte von Abschied und letztendlicher Vernichtung ihrer Besitzerin erzählt und symbolisiert. Und schließlich geht es um den Stellenwert von Puppen und Teddys in verschiedenen Kinderzeitschriften, die – in den politisch unsicheren Zeiten zwischen und nach den beiden Weltkriegen – Identifikationsfiguren und Interaktionspartner für Kinder sein können. &#13;
Ein zweiter Fokus thematisiert Puppen und ihre Narrative im Kontext verschiedener aversiver Erfahrungen sowie in Zeiten psychischer Irritation. So geht es zum einen um die literaturwissenschaftliche Sicht auf die Bedeutung und Wirkung von Puppen in zwei ‚klassischen’ Puppenerzählungen: „"Nussknacker und Mausekönig" von E.T.A. Hoffmann und "Romeo und Julia auf dem Dorfe" von Gottfried Keller. Zum anderen werden in verschiedenen Beiträgen Entgrenzungs-, Transformations- und Identitätsfragen in Mensch-Puppen-Bezügen aus medien- und kunstwissenschaftlicher sowie kinderliterarischer Perspektive angesprochen, in denen Puppen in Gestalt von Androiden, Kunstwesen oder anthropomorphen Figuren agieren und dabei selber Irritationen auslösen oder Versuche darstellen, Antworten auf beunruhigende Fragen zu finden.&#13;
Über den Themenschwerpunkt hinaus finden sich zudem eine Reihe weiterer Beitragsformen zu verschiedenen puppenbezogenen Themen und Praxen, die noch einmal das breite Spektrum unterschiedlicher Puppen-Narrative und Zugangsformen dokumentieren: So beschäftigt sich ein freier Beitrag mit dem Puppenspiel als strukturiertes Therapieangebot für Kinder, bei den Miszellen findet sich eine Skizze zu Marlene Dietrich und ihren Puppen sowie ein kurzer Essay zu einer biographischen Erinnerung, ein Interview mit der Begründerin des Berliner Puppentheaters bubales veranschaulicht Möglichkeiten der dramatischen und poetischen Umsetzung von Puppen-Themen, im Diskussionsforum wird ein kritischer Blick auf "Barbie als Diskursmaschine" geworfen und eine Rezension zum Ausstellungskatalog "From Her Wooden Sleep von Ydessa Hendels" lotet Chancen und Grenzen der künstlerischen Arbeit mit Puppen-Artefakten aus.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">Dolls / Puppets in Threat Scenarios – this is the topic focus of the first issue of the interdisciplinary online magazine "denkste: puppe / just a bit of: doll" on human-doll discourses (acronym: de: do). The term ’doll’ stands for anthropomorphic ’beings’ and artifacts of all kinds and the concept of threat is broadly defined. This focus was stimulated by the assumption that dolls and doll-related artifacts are of particular importance in times of existential threat as well as in phases of inner psychic anxiety and irritation. Yet, the basically ambiguous character of the doll does not necessarily determine a clear effect, so that its usability always involves a certain blurriness and ambivalence. In threatening and adverse situations dolls can act as companions and significant (transitional) objects, thus allowing psychic stabilization, security, and attachment as well as enabling (inner) autonomy, agency, and developmental processes. But dolls can also be a crucial component of threat scenarios themselves and act frightening in this function. All this applies not only to material and real existing dolls and puppets, but also to dolls as literary and / or media figures as well as to doll narratives of any kind. The articles included here come from different disciplines and open up an appealing and deliberately non-disciplinary oriented human-doll discourse from multiple perspectives. Accordingly, the relevant themes as well as the respective methodological approaches are highly heterogeneous. Thus, some contributions follow the long tradition of doll narratives in literature while others discuss currrent topics and discourses on future scenarios and new technologies by means of various doll-related media formats and / or art performances. &#13;
A first thematic focus is on the significance of dolls in experiencing threats and losses in the context of war, flight and persecution in times of political uncertainty. Here, different facets of threat scenarios are addressed from different disciplinary perspectives. From the field of object and material theater two productions are introduced in which menacing war scenes are processed by means of plastic dolls or amorphous material. From a psychological perspective, dolls are discussed in their roles and functions as transitional objects within the context of upheaval, war and violence. Furthermore, two literary contributions analyze novels from children’s and youth literature. One story deals with a doll which contributes to the psychological stabilization of the literary protagonist. The other story tells of a girl and her doll which symbolizes the final farewell and eventual annihilation of the (Jewish) girl. Finally, the role of dolls and teddy bears in various children’s magazines is exemplified, which serve as identification figures and interaction partners for children in the politically unstable times between and after the two World Wars.&#13;
A second focus deals with dolls and their narratives in the context of various aversive experiences as well as in times of psychological irritation. Two contributions analyze the meaning and effect of dolls in two ’classical’ doll narratives from a literary perspective: "Nussknacker und Mausekönig" by E.T.A. Hoffmann and "Romeo und Julia auf dem Dorfe" by Gottfried Keller. Further contributions address questions of ego dissolution, transformation and identity processes in human-doll relations from various perspectives such as media, art and children’s literature. Here, dolls appear as androids, artistic or anthropomorphic figures which cause irritation themselves or attempt to find answers to disturbing human-doll questions. &#13;
In addition to the main topic, there are also a number of other sections and types of contributions on various doll-related topics and practices which once again document the wide range of doll narratives and possible forms of access: For example, a free contribution deals with doll play as a structured therapy for children, the miscellaneous section includes a portrait of Marlene Dietrich and her dolls as well as a short essay on a biographical reminiscence, an interview with the founder of the Berlin Puppet Theater bubales illustrates the possibilities of dramatic and poetic realization of puppet and doll narratives, a critical view on "Barbie as a discourse machine" is presented in the discussion forum and a review of the exhibition catalog "From Her Wooden Sleep by Ydessa Hendels" explores opportunities and limits of artistic work with doll artifacts.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2018</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">PeriodicalPart</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-13212</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">ger</dc:language>
   <dcterms:isPartOf xsi:type="ddb:ZSTitelID">5</dcterms:isPartOf>
   <dcterms:isPartOf xsi:type="ddb:ZS-Ausgabe">2018(1), S. -</dcterms:isPartOf>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="puppen_in_bedrohungsszenarien.pdf" ddb:fileSize="20638324"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">2dd0e107ae8f64c86d03ed5dae77eacd</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/1321/1/puppen_in_bedrohungsszenarien.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/1321</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>