<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>1328</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Crossover literature and age in crisis at the turn of the 21st century : Harry Potter’s kidults and the Twilight moms</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Maria Verena</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Peters</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Cross-over &lt;Literatur&gt;</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">All Age Literatur</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Kinder- und Jugendliteratur</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Harry Potter</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Twilight</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">All age literature</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Crossover literature</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Harry Potter</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Twilight</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">800</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">At the turn of the 21st century, the widely visible popularity of children’s and young adult literature with adult readers lead literary and social critics to ask whether the inhabitants of Western culture were refusing to grow up. Whilst books had been crossing over the line between the adult and children’s book market ever since the separation into two markets had been introduced, the perceived rise in this traffic led to a felt crisis concerning age and identity. At the example of the Harry Potter and the Twilight novels, Maria Verena Peters analyzes the discourse about childhood, coming of age and adulthood inside and outside the pages of children’s and young adult literature as the 20th century came to an end and a new millennium was beginning. Her analysis suggests that this discourse was determined by an anxiety that without the patriarchal, heterosexual, nuclear family, age cannot serve to produce meaningful identity categories. Beyond the policing of gender and sexuality, the discourse of age in crisis – as the examples of Harry Potter’s kidults and the Twilight moms serve to show – also functions to naturalize notions of class and consumption. In addition to the prominent two novel series of the title, the PhD thesis covers a wide range of popular culture artefacts, from Near Dark to Buffy the Vampire Slayer and from The Big Bang Theory to Hotter than my Daughter. It builds upon key findings of fan studies to uncover the intersectionality of age, gender, class and consumption in the marketing, reception and critique of children’s and young adult literature.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Um die letzte Jahrhundertwende sorgte die erhöhte Sichtbarkeit der Popularität von Kinder- und Jugendliteratur bei einer erwachsenen Leserschaft dafür, dass Literatur- und Gesellschaftskritiker die Frage stellten, ob die westliche Gesellschaft sich weigere erwachsen zu werden. Obgleich Bücher über die Grenze zwischen dem Segment für Kinder und dem für Erwachsene hin und her gewandert waren seit der Buchmarkt in diese zwei Hälften geteilt worden war, sorgte der Eindruck eines Anstiegs dieser Grenzüberschreitungen für das Gefühl einer Krise von Alter und Identität. Am Beispiel der Harry Potter- und Twilight-Romane analysiert Maria Verena Peters den Diskurs über Kindheit, Erwachsen-Werden und Erwachsen-Sein um die Wende vom 20. zum 21. Jahrhundert diesseits und jenseits der Romanwelten von Rowling und Meyer. Ihre Analyse fördert zu Tage, dass dieser Diskurs von einer Angst gekennzeichnet ist, dass Alter ohne das Konstrukt der patriarchalen, weißen, heterosexuellen, nuklearen Familie keine bedeutungsvollen Identitätskategorien stiften kann. Abgesehen vom Regulieren von Geschlechterrollen und Sexualität naturalisiert der Diskurs von Alter in der Krise auch die soziale Klasse und den Konsum, wie die Beispiele der „Kidults“ im Zusammenhang mit Harry Potter und der sogenannten „Twilight Moms“ zeigen. Zusätzlich zu den titelstiftenden zwei Romanreihen behandelt diese Dissertationsschrift eine weite Bandbreite popkultureller Artefakte, wie z.B. Near Dark, The Big Bang Theory, Buffy the Vampire Slayer und Hotter than my Daughter. Aufbauend auf den Erkenntnissen der fan studies wird die Intersektionalität von Alter, Geschlechterrollen, Klasse und Konsum in der Vermarktung, Rezeption und Kritik von Kinder- und Jugendliteratur aufgezeigt.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2015-03-19</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2018</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-13280</dc:identifier>
   <dc:source xsi:type="ddb:ISBN">978-3-96182-013-9</dc:source>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dcterms:isPartOf xsi:type="ddb:noScheme">Reihe Medienwissenschaften;  15</dcterms:isPartOf>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät I Philosophische Fakultät</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Dissertation_Maria_Verena_Peters.pdf" ddb:fileSize="1400937"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">8348c03ec20e9412556694f2deafac70</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/1328/1/Dissertation_Maria_Verena_Peters.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/1328</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>