<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>1369</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">QCD factorisation in exclusive semileptonic B decays : new applications and resummation of rapidity logarithms</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">QCD Faktorisierung in exklusiven semileptonischen B Zerfällen : neue Anwendungen und Resummation von Rapiditätslogarithmen</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Philipp</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Böer</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Semileptonischer Zerfall</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">B-Zerfälle</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">QCD Faktorisierung</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">SCET</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Kollineare Anomalie</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">B-Decays</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">QCD Factorisation</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">SCET</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Collinear Anomaly</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">530</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">Exclusive charmless decays of heavy B-mesons play an important role both in testing the Standard Model of particle physics as well as in searches for new physics. Due to the non-perturbative nature of the strong interactions, reliable predictions for hadronic decay rates are intrinsically difficult to estimate. Exploiting the simplifications of the strong interaction dynamics that arise in the heavy-quark limit, the "QCD factorisation approach" (QCDF) allows for a separation of perturbative and non-perturbative effects in these decays. In this thesis we present new applications of the QCDF approach and investigate cases where the factorisation is not yet understood. In a first project, we introduce a novel factorisation formula for form factors in semileptonic multi-body B → ππlν decays that is valid for large pion energies and a large dipion invariant mass. We present phenomenological implications in the form of approximate form factor relations, which can be used to interpolate between different phase-space regions. Theoretically, a careful consideration of endpoint-divergent moments is crucial in the confirmation of the factorisation formula. They either cancel in factorisable contributions or can be absorbed into simpler and more universal B → π form factors. For the B → π form factors themselves, a complete factorisation of scales is presently not understood as a consequence of ill-defined convolution integrals. We investigate these so-called "endpoint divergences" in a perturbative toy model, in which the hadronic states are approximated as non-relativistic bound states of two heavy quarks. The relativistic QCD dynamics is then calculable in perturbation theory, and by employing the method of regions the factorisation properties can be studied. Fairly new methods that go under the names rapidity renormalisation group and collinear anomaly have been successfully applied to handle endpoint divergences in collider physics observables. In this thesis we apply these techniques to heavy-to-light form factors at large hadronic recoil. As a first step on the way to establish an all-order factorisation theorem, we present an improved factorisation that contains a resummation of all leading logarithms within the perturbative model. Due to operator mixing, the structures that arise in the resummed expression are more complicated but also more interesting than in collider physics applications of these methods.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Exklusive Zerfälle schwerer B-Mesonen in leichte Mesonen spielen eine wichtige Rolle, um das Standardmodell der Elementarteilchenphysik zu testen, sowie nach Neuer Physik zu suchen. Aufgrund der nicht-perturbativen Natur der starken Wechselwirkung sind verlässliche Vorhersagen für hadronische Observablen schwer zu bestimmen. Vereinfachungen der Dynamik treten jedoch im Limes unendlich großer Masse des b-Quarks auf. Darauf basierend erlaubt der "QCD Faktorisierungsansatz" (QCDF) eine systematische Trennung von perturbativen und nicht-perturbativen Effekten in oben genannten Zerfällen. In dieser Arbeit präsentieren wir neue Anwendungen des QCDF Zugangs und untersuchen im Speziellen Fälle, in denen die Faktorisierung noch unverstanden ist. In einem ersten Projekt führen wir ein neues Faktorisierungstheorem für die Formfaktoren in semileptonischen B → ππlν Zerfällen ein, welches für große Pionenergien sowie für große invariante Masse des Dipion Systems gültig ist. Phänomenologische Implikationen in Form von näherungsweise gültigen Relationen zwischen den Formfaktoren werden untersucht, und konnen in zukünftigen Studien genutzt werden, um zwischen verschiedenen Phasenraumregionen zu interpolieren. In der Herleitung des Faktorisierungstheorems spielen endpunkt-divergente Momente eine entscheidende Rolle. Diese heben sich teilweise zwischen verschiedenen Beiträgen weg, oder aber konnen in universellere B → π Formfaktoren absorbiert werden. Eine vollständige Faktorisierung von Skalen in den B → π Formfaktoren ist aufgrund von divergenten Faltungsintegralen derzeit noch unverstanden. Wir untersuchen diese sogenannten Endpunktdivergenzen in einem storungstheoretischen Modell, in welchem die hadronischen Zustände als nicht-relativistische Bindungszustände zweier schwerer Quarks genähert werden konnen. Die relativistische Dynamik ist dann storungstheoretisch berechenbar und die Faktorisierungseigenschaften konnen mit Hilfe der Methode der Regionen untersucht werden. In dieser Arbeit wenden wir die neuen Methoden der "kollinearen Anomalie" sowie der "Rapiditäts-Renormierungsgruppe", welche bisher noch nicht im Kontext der Flavourphysik benutzt wurden, auf die Formfaktoren in exklusiven schwer-nach-leicht Prozessen an. Als ersten Schritt auf dem Weg, ein Faktorisierungstheorem zu etablieren, wird eine verbesserte Faktorisierung der Formfaktoren in diesem Modell präsentiert, welche eine Resummation von allen führenden großen Logarithmen beinhaltet. Aufgrund von mehreren Operatoren, welche untereinander mischen, ist unser Ergebnis komplizierter als in Anwendungen dieser Methoden in der Collider Physik.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2018-08-23</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2018</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-13694</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät IV - Naturwissenschaftlich-Technische Fakultät</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Dissertation_Philipp_Boeer.pdf" ddb:fileSize="2575692"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">8fa764ff3c9ba330fae3eb520f4a44ad</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/1369/1/Dissertation_Philipp_Boeer.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/1369</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>