<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>1393</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">A test for the existence of protons in ultra-high energy cosmic rays</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Ein Test auf die Existenz von Protonen in ultrahochenergetischer kosmischer Strahlung</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Philipp</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Heimann</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Kosmische Strahlung</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Gumbelverteilung</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Cosmic rays</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Protons</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Lorentz invariance</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Gumbel distribution</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">530</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">The determination of the composition of cosmic rays at ultra-high energies is still a challenge in astroparticle physics. Beside of the determination of the overall composition the knowledge of the general existence of single elements, specifically protons, is sufficient for certain analyses. This work presents a method which is able to reject the helium origin of single very deep air shower events. Utilizing a parametrized distribution of shower maxima, predicted by different hadronic interaction models and CONEX, it is possible to determine a probability value of a helium nucleus to induce an air shower with the observed depth of shower maximum or deeper. If this derived probability value is small enough, the hypothesis of a helium primary can be rejected. Since heavier primaries than helium tend to produce air showers with lower depths than Helium, which leads to smaller probabilities for deep events, these possible primaries can be excluded as well. After the development of the method, a check of the method’s performance is presented and a first application to the data of the Pierre Auger Observatory is performed. The result shows that this method might be able to exclude the helium origin hypothesis with good significance.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Die Bestimmung der Massenkomposition der kosmischen Strahlung bei höchsten Energien gehört immer noch zu den Herausforderungen der modernen Astroteilchenphysik. Neben der Bestimmung der Gesamtkomposition kann es für einige Analysen ausreichen, die Existenz bestimmter Primärteilchen bei einer bestimmten Energie nachzuweisen. In dieser Arbeit wird eine Methode präsentiert, die die Parametrisierung der Verteilung der Tiefe des Maximums von Luftschauern, vorhergesagt durch CONEX für verschiedene hadronische Interaktionsmodelle, nutzt, um eine Wahrscheinlichkeit zu bestimmen, dass ein primärer Heliumkern einen Luftschauer mit der beobachteten Tiefe des Maximums oder tiefer auslöst. Wenn diese Wahrscheinlichkeit klein genug ist, kann die Hypothese eines primären Heliumkerns verworfen werden. Da noch schwerere Primärteilchen dazu tendieren Luftschauer mit kleineren Tiefen des Schauermaximums zu produzieren, können ebenso diese schweren Teilchen ausgeschlossen werden. Nach der Beschreibung der entwickelten Methode wird ein kurzer Test ihrer Leistungsfähigkeit präsentiert, bevor sie dann eine erste Anwendung auf Daten des Pierre Auger Observatoriums findet. Diese erste Anwendung zeigt, dass die Methode in der Lage sein kann, die Helium Hypothese mit guter Signifikanz auszuschließen.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2018-10-02</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2018</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-13935</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät IV - Naturwissenschaftlich-Technische Fakultät</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Dissertation_Philipp_Heimann.pdf" ddb:fileSize="23210204"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">4e7d95cbb10a47ccfcc60e5d1b65b4a8</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/1393/1/Dissertation_Philipp_Heimann.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/1393</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>