<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>1421</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Spin-weighted spherical harmonics and their application for the construction of tensor slepian functions on the spherical cap</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Spin-gewichtete Kugelflächenfunktionen und ihre Anwendung zur Konstruktion von tensoriellen Slepian-Funktionen auf der sphärischen Kappe</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Katrin</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Seibert</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Kugelflächenfunktion</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Spin-gewichtete Kugelflächenfunktionen</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Slepian-Funktionen</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">sphärische Kappe</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">spin-weighted spherical harmonics</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Slepian functions</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">commuting operator</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">spherical cap</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">510</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">The spin-weighted spherical harmonics of Newman and Penrose (1966) form an orthonormal basis of LÂ²(Ω) on the unit sphere Ω and have a huge field of applications. We present a unified mathematical theory, which implies the collection of already known properties of the spin-weighted spherical harmonics, recapitulated in a mathematical way, and connected to the notation of the spherical harmonics. In addition, we use spin-weighted spherical harmonics to construct tensor Slepian functions on the sphere. Slepian functions are spatially concentrated and spectrally limited. For scalar and vectorial data on the sphere, they are utilized in a variety of disciplines, including geodesy, cosmology, and biomedical imaging. Their concentration within a chosen region of the sphere allows for local inversions when only regional data are available, or enable the extraction of regional information. We focus on the analysis of tensorial fields, as collected e.g.~in the GOCE mission, by means of Slepian functions. For tensorial data, Slepian functions have already been constructed by Eshagh (2009) in the basis of the tensor spherical harmonics of Martinec (2003). By using spin-weighted spherical harmonics, our theory offers several numerical advantages. Furthermore, we present a method for an efficient construction of tensor Slepian functions for spherical caps. In this context, we are able to construct a localized basis on the spherical cap for the cosmic microwave background (CMB) polarization.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Die spin-gewichteten Kugelflächenfunktionen, definiert von Newman und Penrose (1966), bilden eine Orthonormalbasis des LÂ²(Ω) auf der Einheitssphäre Ω und haben ein breit gefächertes Anwendungsgebiet. Wir präsentieren eine einheitliche mathematische Theorie der spin-gewichteten Kugelflächenfunktionen inklusive Auflistung ihrer bereits bekannten Eigenschaften auf mathematische Weise, verknüpft mit der Notation der Theorie der Kugelflächenfunktionen. Des Weiteren verwenden wir die spin-gewichteten Kugelflächenfunktionen zur Konstruktion tensorieller Slepian-Funktionen auf der Sphäre. Slepian-Funktionen sind räumlich konzentriert und spektral begrenzt. Für skalare und vektorielle Messdaten auf der Sphäre werden sie in diversen Bereichen wie Geodäsie, Kosmologie und der biomedizinischen Bildgebung verwendet. Ihre Konzentriertheit in einer ausgewählten Region auf der Sphäre ermoglicht die lokale Inversion, wenn nur regionale Messdaten gegeben sind oder ermoglichen es, regionale Information zu extrahieren. Wir konzentrieren uns auf die Analyse von Tensorfeldern mit Hilfe von Slepian-Funktionen, wie sie z.B. von der Satellitenmission GOCE stammen. Unsere Konstruktion mit spin-gewichteten Kugelflächenfunktionen erzielt für tensorwertige Felder diverse numerische Vorteile und erlaubt eine effizientere Konstruktion der tensoriellen Slepian-Funktionen für sphärische Kappen, z.B. eine lokale Basis auf der sphärischen Kappe für die Polarisation der kosmischen Hintergrundstrahlung (CMB).</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2018-05-16</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2018</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-14210</dc:identifier>
   <dc:source xsi:type="ddb:ISBN">978-3-96182-028-3</dc:source>
   <dc:source xsi:type="ddb:noScheme">Zugl.: Siegen : universi - Universitätsverlag Siegen, 2018. - ISBN 978-3-96182-028-3</dc:source>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät IV - Naturwissenschaftlich-Technische Fakultät</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Dissertation_Katrin_Seibert.pdf" ddb:fileSize="11981099"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">4d0ce3ac5867a5addb8f817c450844b9</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/1421/1/Dissertation_Katrin_Seibert.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/1421</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>