<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>1432</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">The influence of microstructure on the fracture behaviour of ferritic ODS steels</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Einfluss der Mikrostruktur auf das Bruchverhalten von ferritischen ODS-Stählen</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Aniruddh</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Das</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">ODS</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Bruchmechanik</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Risswachstum</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">ODS steel</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Nanostructured ferritic alloys</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Fracture behaviour</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Secondary cracking</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">620</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Oxidverfestigte Stähle (ODS) sind als Hüllmaterial für Brennstäbe in Generation IV Kernreaktoren und als Strukturmaterial in Fusionsreaktoren vorgesehen. Die Bruchzähigkeit ist ein wesentlicher Parameter für die Bewertung der strukturellen Integrität und die Bearbeitbarkeit. Ungeachtet einer guten Festigkeit bei hohen Temperaturen und einer guten Beständigkeit gegenüber bestrahlungsinduziertem Schwellen haben ODS-Stähle im Vergleich zu konventionellen martensitisch-ferritischen Cr-Stählen eine niedrige Bruchzähigkeit. Sowohl gewalzte als auch warm stranggepresste ODS-Stähle zeigen ein anisotropes Bruchverhalten. Zusätzlich treten Sekundärrisse auf, welche zu einem Versagen der Struktur führen können. &#13;
In der vorliegenden Arbeit werden die mikrostrukturellen Merkmale, welche für die niedrige Bruchzähigkeit verantwortlich sind, das anisotrope Bruchverhalten und das Auftreten von Sekundärrissen untersucht. Diese Informationen sind zur Verbesserung der Brucheigenschaften für Hersteller von ODS-Stählen von großer Bedeutung. Von drei ODS-Stählen wurden mit Miniatur-Kompaktzugproben Risswiderstandskurven mit dem Teilentlastungsverfahren gemessen und daraus Bruchzähigkeiten nach ASTM E1820 ermittelt. Die Mikrostruktur, die Bruchflächen und die Rissausbreitung wurden mit dem Raster- und Transmissionselektronenmikroskop und Elektronenrückstreubeugung untersucht und das Bruchverhalten charakterisiert. Eine quantitative Bewertung der die Bruchzähigkeit beeinflussenden mikrostrukturellen Parameter wird mit einer auf der kritischen Dehnung basierenden Beziehung der Bruchzähigkeit vorgenommen.&#13;
Es wurde beobachtet, dass die niedrige Bruchzähigkeit in erster Linie durch die Haftfestigkeit zwischen porenbildenden Teilchen und der Matrix bestimmt wird. Die Größe und der Abstand der &#13;
porenbildenden Teilchen haben zusammen mit der Fließfestigkeit keinen dominanten Einfluss auf die Bruchzähigkeit. Es wurde festgestellt, dass das anisotrope Bruchverhalten der ODS-Stähle in erster Linie durch die anisotrope Struktur der Körner hervorgerufen wird. Kristallographische Anisotropie und Ausrichtung der Poren bildenden Teilchen haben keinen wesentlichen Einfluss auf das Bruchverhalten. Sekundärrisse treten durch den hohen Grad der Anisotropie bevorzugt bei warmgewalzten Material auf. Sie können das Wachsen des Hauptrisses und das Auftreten von Spaltbruch beeinflussen. Sekundärrisse entstehen vor der Ausbreitung des Hauptrisses bei geringerer Belastung.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">Oxide dispersion strengthened (ODS) steels are candidate materials for cladding tube and structural components in Generation IV nuclear fission reactors and as candidate materials for structural components in fusion devices. Fracture toughness is an important parameter required for the structural integrity and workability of a material. Despite having high strength at high temperatures and high irradiation swelling resistance, ODS steels have been known to possess lower fracture toughness than non-ODS ferritic martensitic steels, their immediate competitor. They also exhibit anisotropic fracture behaviour, especially for the hot-rolled and hot-extruded variants. In addition, ODS steels tend to form secondary cracks, which absorb energy but can lead to design problems. &#13;
In the present work, the microstructural features which cause low fracture toughness, anisotropic fracture behaviour and secondary cracking are investigated. This information can help manufacturers develop ODS steels with better fracture properties. Fracture toughness testing on three different batches of ODS steels are performed using miniature fracture toughness C(T) specimens using the unloading compliance method. The basic microstructure, fracture surfaces and crack propagation are investigated using techniques such as SEM, TEM and EBSD and compared with the fracture behaviour. A quantitative assessment of the microstructural parameters affecting fracture toughness is made using a critical strain based fracture toughness expression. &#13;
It was observed that the low fracture toughness of ODS steels is predominantly affected by the bond strength between the void initiating particle and the matrix. The size and inter-particle spacing of void initiating particles along with the yield stress did not dominantly affect the fracture toughness. The anisotropic fracture behaviour in ODS steels was found to be predominantly affected by the anisotropic grain morphology. Crystallographic anisotropy and anisotropy in void initiating particle distribution did not dominantly affect the fracture anisotropy. Secondary cracking favoured hot-rolled over hot-extruded specimens due to higher degree of microstructural anisotropy. Secondary cracks could stabilize primary crack propagation as well as prevent cleavage fracture at low temperatures. However, the drawback with secondary cracks was that they initiated earlier or at lower loads than the primary crack.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2018-12-17</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2018</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-14329</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Dissertation_Aniruddh_Das.pdf" ddb:fileSize="12621998"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">e478fb3a20de0334c178ed59747b0e4a</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/1432/1/Dissertation_Aniruddh_Das.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/1432</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>