<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>1509</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Quantum hypergraph states and the theory of multiparticle entanglement</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" ddb:type="translated" lang="ger">Quanten-Hypergraph-Zustände und die Theorie der Mehrteilchen-Verschränkung</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Mariami</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Gachechiladze</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Quanteninformatik</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Quantentheorie</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Mehrteilchen Verschränkung</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Quantum Information</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Quantum theory</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Multiparticle entanglement</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Hypergraph states</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Bell-inequalities</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">530</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">This thesis is devoted to learning different aspects of quantum entanglement theory.&#13;
More precisely, it concerns a characterization of certain classes of pure multipartite&#13;
entangled states, their nonlocal and entanglement properties, comparisons with the&#13;
other well-studied classes of states and, finally, their utilization in certain quantum&#13;
information processing tasks.&#13;
&#13;
The most extensive part of the thesis explores an interesting class of pure multipartite&#13;
entangled states, quantum hypergraph states. These states are generalizations of the&#13;
renowned class of graph states. Here we cover their nonlocal properties in various&#13;
scenarios, derive graphical rules for unitary transformations and Pauli bases measurements.&#13;
Using these rules, we characterize entanglement classes of hypergraph states&#13;
under local operations, obtain tight entanglement witnesses, and calculate entanglement&#13;
measures for hypergraph states. Finally, we apply all the aforementioned analysis&#13;
to endorse hypergraph states as powerful resource states for measurement-based&#13;
quantum computation and quantum error-correction.&#13;
&#13;
The rest of the thesis is devoted to three disjoint problems, but all of them are still in&#13;
the scope of entanglement theory. First, using mathematical structure of linear matrix&#13;
pencils, we coarse grain entanglement in tripartite pure states of local dimensions&#13;
2 x m x n under the most general local transformations. In addition, we identify the&#13;
structure of generic states for every m and n and see that for certain dimensions there&#13;
is a resemblance between bipartite and tripartite entanglement. Second, we consider&#13;
the following question: Can entanglement detection be improved, if in addition to&#13;
the expectation value of the measured witness, we have knowledge of the expectation&#13;
value of another observable? For low dimensions we give necessary and sufficient&#13;
criterion that such two product observables must satisfy in order to be able to detect&#13;
entanglement. Finally, we derive a general statement that any genuine N-partite entangled&#13;
state can always be projected on any of its k-partite subsystems in a way that&#13;
the new state in genuine k-partite entangled.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Diese Arbeit ist verschiedenen Aspekten der Verschränkungstheorie gewidmet. Genauer&#13;
gesagt, beschäftigt sie sich mit der Charakterisierung verschiedener Klassen&#13;
reiner mehrteilchenverschränkter Zustände, sowie ihrer nicht-lokalen und Verschränkungseigenschaften,&#13;
Vergleichen mit anderen bekannten Klassen von Zuständen und,&#13;
letztendlich, ihrer Verwendung in der Quanteninformationsverarbeitung.&#13;
&#13;
Der größte Teil dieser Arbeit beschäftigt sich mit einer interessanten Klasse von reinen&#13;
mehrteilchenverschränkten Zuständen, den Hypergraphen Zuständen. Diese Zustände&#13;
bilden eine Verallgemeinerung der weithin bekannten Graphen Zustände. Wir&#13;
werden ihre nicht-lokalen Eigenschaften untersuchen und graphische Regeln für ihr&#13;
Verhalten unter unitären Transformationen sowie Messungen in der Pauli Basis herleiten.&#13;
Unter Verwendung dieser Regeln werden Verschränkungsklassen unter lokalen&#13;
Operationen charakterisiert, und optimale Verschränkungszeugen sowie Verschränkungsmaße&#13;
berechnet. Zuletzt wird, unter Berücksichtigung der vorangegangenen&#13;
Analyse, gezeigt, dass Hypergraphen Zustände eine Ressource für Messungsbasierte&#13;
Quantencomputer und Quantenfehlerkorrektur bilden.&#13;
&#13;
Der verbleibende Teil dieser Arbeit beschäftigt sich mit drei unterschiedlichen Problemen&#13;
im Rahmen der Verschränkungstheorie. Zuerst wird die Verschränkung reiner&#13;
Dreiteilchenzustände mit lokalen Dimensionen 2 x m x n unter den allgemeinsten&#13;
Transformationen untersucht. Dazu wird eine spezielle mathematische Struktur verwendet,&#13;
die so genannten Matrix Pencils. Zudem identifizieren wir die Struktur von&#13;
generischen Zuständen für alle m und n und wir werden sehen, dass in bestimmten&#13;
Dimensionen eine Ähnlichkeit zwischen Zweiteilchen- und Dreiteilchenverschränkung&#13;
besteht. Danach wird der Frage nachgegangen: Kann Verschränkungsdetektion&#13;
verbessert werden, wenn man zusätzlich zum Erwartungswertes des Verschränkungszeugen&#13;
noch den Erwartungswert einer anderen Observablen kennt? Für niedrige Dimensionen&#13;
werden notwendige und hinreichende Bedingungen hergeleitet, die zwei&#13;
Produktobservablen erfüllen müssen um Verschränkung detektieren zu können. Zuletzt&#13;
wird die allgemeine Aussage bewiesen, dass jeder echte N-Teilchen verschränkte&#13;
&#13;
Zustand immer auf seine k-Teilchen Subsysteme projiziert werden kann, sodass dieser&#13;
Zustand echt k-Teilchen verschränkt ist.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dc:contributor xsi:type="pc:Contributor" thesis:role="referee">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Otfried</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Gühne</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:contributor>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2019-08-26</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2019</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-15090</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät IV - Naturwissenschaftlich-Technische Fakultät</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Dissertation_Mariami_Gachechiladze.pdf" ddb:fileSize="2246096"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">bf0c4a7d9e1f9b0985374562e81aa029</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/1509/2/Dissertation_Mariami_Gachechiladze.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/1509</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>