<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>1556</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">X-ray structural characterization of individual as-grown GaAs/(In,Ga)As/(GaAs) based core-multi-shell nanowires</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Ali</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Al Hassan</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Röntgendiffraktometrie</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Core-shell nanowires</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Nano X-ray diffraction</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Structural and optical properties</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">530</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">In recent years, owing to the major development of X-ray focusing optics such as fresnel zone plates and Kirkpatrick-Baez mirrors, highly intense and collimated X-ray beams with spot sizes in the range of a hundred nanometers and below can be achieved. Together with proper sample preparation such as selective area growth, X-ray diffraction techniques can be deployed to study single nanometer-sized objects, in particular nanowires. Typically, transmission electron microscopy based methods are used to investigate the thickness, crystal phase and alloy distribution in individual core-shell nanowires. These properties, if controlled precisely, play the key role in optimizing the optical emission of NW based devices. Nevertheless, in this work, using X-ray nano diffraction based techniques we demonstrate a new path to achieve the complete structural characterization of individual as-grown GaAs/(In,Ga)As/GaAs based core-shell nanowires in addition to correlating their phase structure to their optical properties.&#13;
In a first step, the spatial distribution of the In alloy within the (In,Ga)As shell of individual GaAs/(In,Ga)As based core-shell nanowires is inspected by means of nano-focused scanning X-ray fluorescence microscopy. In contrast to energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy in transmission electron microscopy, using this fast probing technique one can probe several nanowires in their as-grown geometry without the need of a complicated sample preparation procedure.&#13;
In a second step, high resolution X-ray nano diffraction is applied along and perpendicular to the NW [111] growth direction to measure the structural properties of individual GaAs/(In,Ga)As/GaAs core-shell nanowires grown by vapor liquid solid epitaxy. There, we were able to calculate the thickness of the core and shells and therefore reconstruct the full NW cross-section which is forever done by means of transmission electron microscopy of the nanowire basal plane.&#13;
In a third step, monitoring the GaAs 111 Bragg reflection, scanning X-ray diffraction microscopy was used as a fast scanning technique to reveal the polytype distribution along the growth axes of several individual core-multi-shell nanowires. The phase distribution was then correlated with cathodolu-minescence measurements revealing an enhancement in the optical emission of a mixed phase formed of the cubic zinc blende crystal phase and its twin, the hexagonal wurtzite polytype and slabs of defects and stacking faults.&#13;
Finally, we reveal induced structural and optical damage of individual semi-conductor nanowires, that are supposed to be resistant to radiation, for a threshold absorbed X-ray dose. This was demonstrated only for measurements that require fixing the X-ray nano beam to the same position along the nanowire growth axis. This study will spreads awareness regarding time consuming X-ray diffraction measurements performed on nano-structures.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Dank der herausragenden Innovationen der letzten Jahre auf dem Gebiet der Röntgenoptiken, wie z.B. der Fresnel Zonenplatten und Kirkpatrick-Baez Spiegelsystemen, kann man heute intensive Röntgenstrahlung auf eine Spotgröße von hundert Nanometer und weniger fokussieren. Unter Berücksichtigung spezifischer Methoden der Probenpräparation, wie dem Wachstum auf vorstrukturierten Oberflächen, konnten so neuartige Röntgenbeugungsmethoden zur Untersuchung einzelner Nanoobjekten, wie auch Nanodrähten, entwickelt werden. Bisher wurde vor allem die Transmissionselektronenmikroskopie zur Bestimmung der Dicke, Kristallphase und Elementeverteilung in einzelnen Kern- Mantel Nanodrähten verwendet. Diese Parameter, wenn sie präsise kontrolliert werden, spielen im Prozess der Optimierung der optischen Emission von Nanodraht basierten Bauelementen eine herausragende Rolle. In der vorliegenden Arbeit demonstrieren wir einen neuen Weg der vollständigen Charakterisierung individueller GaAs/(In,Ga)As/GaAs Kern-Mantel Nanodrähten in ihrer Position auf dem Substrat unter Verwendung der Röntgen-Nanodiffraktion, inklusive der Korrelation ihrer strukturellen und optischen Eigenschaften.&#13;
In einem ersten Schritt wurde die räumliche Verteilung von Indium in der (In,Ga)As Schale einzelner GaAs/(In,Ga)As basierter Kern-Mantel Nanodrähte mittels nano-fokussierter Scanning-Röntgen Fluoreszenzmikroskopie bestimmt. Im Gegensatz zur energie-dispersiven Röntgenspektroskopie in Transmissionselektronenmikroskopen kann man mittels nanoTRF mehrere Nanodrähte in ihrer Position auf dem Substrat sehr schnell und ohne vorherige Probenpräparation untersuchen.&#13;
In einem zweiten Schritt wurde die hochauflösende Röntgen- Nanodiffraktion verwendet, um die strukturellen Eigenschaften einzelner, mit Hilfe der Vapour-Liquid-Solid Epitaxie gewachsenen, GaAs/(In,Ga)As/GaAs Kern-Mantel Nanodrähte parallel und senkrecht zur [111] Wachstumsrichtung vermessen. Damit war es möglich, die Dicke des Kerns und der Schalen und den Nanodrahtquerschnitt zu bestimmen, was bisher nur mittels Elektronenmikroskopie an der Nanodraht Basalflächen möglich war.&#13;
In einem dritten Schritt verfolgten wir mittels Scanning Röntgendiffraktometrie den GaAs 111 Bragg Reflex, um die Verteilung der verschiedenen Polytype entlang der Wachstumsachse einzelner Nanodrähte zu bestimmen. Die gemessene Phasenverteilung wurde mit der Ortsabhängigkeit der Kathodolumineszenz korreliert. Es zeigte sich, dass die räumliche bestimmte Erhöhung der optischen Lumineszenz mit einer aus Zinkblende, verzwillingter Zinkblende und Wurtzite Einheiten gemixten Phase zusammenfällt, die außerdem Defektebenen und Stapelfehler enthalten.&#13;
Zuletzt bestimmten wir die strukturelle und optische Degeneration als Funktion der absorbierten Strahlungsdosis in einzelnen Halbleiter Nanodrähten, die bisher als Strahlungsresistent galten. Die beschriebenen Schäden waren nur dann nachweisbar, wenn ein Nanostrahl über längere Zeit die gleiche Position auf der Achse des Nanodrahtes beleuchtete. Unsere Erkenntnisse sollten in zukünftigen zeitintensiven Röntgenbeugungsexperimenten mit Nanostrahlen Berücksichtigung finden.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dc:contributor xsi:type="pc:Contributor" thesis:role="referee">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Ullrich</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Pietsch</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:contributor>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2019-10-29</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2019</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-15562</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/lizenz.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät IV - Naturwissenschaftlich-Technische Fakultät</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Dissertation_Ali_Al_Hassan.pdf" ddb:fileSize="37525198"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">4f024268ccdec2e43452029fe4c56be1</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/1556/3/Dissertation_Ali_Al_Hassan.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/1556</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>