<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>1668</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Bildung für nachhaltige Entwicklung im Sachunterrichtsstudium</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" ddb:type="translated" lang="ger">Education for sustainable development in primary school teaching</dc:title>
   <dcterms:alternative xsi:type="ddb:talternativeISO639-2" lang="ger">eine empirische Untersuchung zu Einstellungskategorien von Sachunterrichtsstudierenden</dcterms:alternative>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>André</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Dorn</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Bildung für nachhaltige Entwicklung</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Education for sustainable development</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Teacher training</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Primary school</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Concern-based adoption model</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">370</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Um den weltweiten Problemen und Herausforderungen des 21. Jahrhunderts begegnen zu können, nimmt das Leitbild Nachhaltige Entwicklung eine immer bedeutendere Rolle ein. Nicht erst seit der Agenda 21 wird der Bildung im Pro-zess der nachhaltigen Entwicklung eine entscheidende Schlüsselposition zu-gesprochen, denn ohne eine weltweite Bildungsinitiative ist eine nachhaltige Entwicklung nicht gewährleistet. In der Lehramtsausbildung nehmen jedoch Studienangebote zum Bildungskonzept Bildung für nachhaltige Entwicklung immer noch eine untergeordnete Rolle ein. Die Universität Siegen bietet seit der letzten Lehramtsausbildungsreform für Sachunterrichtsstudierende fakul-tativ die Möglichkeit eines perspektivvernetzenden Vertiefungsmoduls (Vertief-tes Studium), in dem schwerpunktmäßig Aspekte einer Nachhaltigen Entwick-lung und einer Bildung für nachhaltige Entwicklung thematisiert werden. &#13;
Die vorliegende Arbeit untersucht, inwiefern sich professionsbezogene Ein-stellungen, Bedürfnisse und Bedenken der angehenden Sachunterrichtslehr-kräfte im Hinblick auf Bildung für nachhaltige Entwicklung während des An-gebotes des Vertiefungsmoduls entwickeln. Grundlage hierfür bildet das Con-cern-Based-Adaption-Model (CBAM) mit der diagnostischen Dimension Stages of Concern (SoC) von Hall und Hord (2011). &#13;
Die Wirksamkeits- und Veränderungsprüfung des Vertieften Studiums erfolgte in einer Begleitstudie mit 109 Sachunterrichtsstudierenden im Rahmen eines Vergleichsgruppendesigns, wobei 42 Studierende das Vertiefte Studium im Sachunterricht belegten. &#13;
Die Ergebnisse weisen auf eine deutliche Entwicklung und Veränderung der Studierenden hinsichtlich ihrer Einstellungsmuster, der Schülerorientierung, der Kooperationsbereitschaft und der Akzeptanz an dem Bildungskonzept Bil-dung für nachhaltige Entwicklung hin. Mit dem Angebot des Vertieften Studi-ums ist es offenbar gelungen, die professionsbezogenen Einstellungen der angehenden Lehrerkräfte positiv zu beeinflussen.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">Teacher training plays a crucial role in the realisation of the concept “Educa-tion for Sustainable Development” (ESD). However, currently only little atten-tion is payed to the implementation of ESD during teacher training. In our study, we examine the attitude change of future primary school teachers of general studies during a facultative course of studies, which focuses on ESD. The study is based on the Stages-of-Concern-Model of Hall &amp; Hord. The re-sults indicate that the facultative course of studies influences the attitudes of students in a positive way and helps to develop desirable profile types.&#13;
In order to meet the global problems and challenges of the 21st century, the concept of sustainable development is playing an increasingly important role. Since well before Agenda 21 education is seen as crucial key position in the process of sustainable development, because without a global education initia-tive sustainable development is not guaranteed. In teacher training, however, study courses concerned with Education for Sustainable Development still play a subordinate role. Since the last teacher training reform (science and so-cial studies at primary school level) for faculty students of general studies, the University of Siegen offers the optional possibility of a perspective-integrating module (in-depth study), which focuses primarily on aspects of sustainable development and education for sustainable development.&#13;
The present study examines the extent to which the professional attitudes, needs and concerns of future teachers of general studies develop during the in-depth study with regard to education for sustainable development. The basis for this is the Concern Based Adaptation Model (CBAM) with the diagnostic dimension Stages of Concern (SoC) of Hall and Hord (2011).&#13;
The examination of the effectiveness of the in-depth-study and the change it caused were carried out in form of an accompanying study with 109 students of general studies in the context of a comparative group design, whereby 42 students took part in the in-depth study of general studies.&#13;
The results indicate a significant development and change of the students who participated in the in-depth study regarding their attitude patterns, their pupil-orientation, their willingness to cooperate and their acceptance of the educa-tional concept Education for Sustainable Development. The in-depth study course has apparently succeeded in positively influencing the profession-related attitudes of the future teachers.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dc:contributor xsi:type="pc:Contributor" thesis:role="referee">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Prof. Dr. Martin</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Gröger</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:contributor>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2020-06-15</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2019</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-16680</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">ger</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/lizenz.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät IV - Naturwissenschaftlich-Technische Fakultät</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Dissertation_Andre_Dorn.pdf" ddb:fileSize="5397703"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">06567d4a14c50e7675b5ce3302918804</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/1668/3/Dissertation_Andre_Dorn.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/1668</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>