<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>1683</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Teilnahme an Arbeit durch technische Assistenz</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" ddb:type="translated" lang="eng">Participation in work through assistive technology : a field study in a sheltered workshop</dc:title>
   <dcterms:alternative xsi:type="ddb:talternativeISO639-2" lang="ger">Eine Feldstudie in einer Werkstatt für behinderte Menschen</dcterms:alternative>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Liane</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Bächler</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Behinderter Mensch</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Menschen mit Behinderung</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Teilnahme an Arbeit</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Inklusion</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Assistenzsysteme</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Werkstatt für behinderte Menschen</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">People with disabilities</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Participation in work</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Inclusion</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Assistive Technology</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Sheltered Workshops</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">360</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Eine umfassende Realisierung gesellschaftlicher Teilnahme für alle Individuen der Bevölkerung stellt sich als spezifische Herausforderung dar, bei der sich die Arbeitswelt als eine wichtige Sphäre erweist. &#13;
Trotz normativer Bezugspunkte durch sozialpolitische Neuerungen sind davon insbesondere Menschen mit geistiger Behinderung und hohem Unterstützungsbedarf ausgeschlossen. Selbst in Werkstätten für behinderte Menschen erfährt diese Personengruppe einen Ausschluss von Teilnahme an Arbeit, da sich auch in diesen, vor dem Hintergrund der aktuellen Herausforderungen der Lebens- und Arbeitswelt des 21. Jahrhunderts, die produktionsseitigen Anforderungen sowie deren betriebswirtschaftliche Ausrichtung verschärfen. &#13;
Menschen mit geistiger Behinderung und hohem Unterstützungsbedarf geraten dadurch in den Hintergrund aktueller Inklusionsbemühungen und erfahren – trotz gesetzlicher Aufforderung – keine adäquate Unterstützung zur Teilnahme an Arbeit.&#13;
Um der Fahrlässigkeit und billigenden Inkaufnahme der Deprivation von einem Großteil der Werkstattbeschäftigten – im Sinne einer gesellschaftlichen Zugehörigkeit durch Teilnahme an Arbeit – entgegenzuwirken, gilt es Gestaltungsoptionen zur Öffnung einer Förderung der Teilnahme an Arbeit für diese umfassend zu betrachten.&#13;
Auf Grundlage einer Feldstudie – unter Einsatz differenzierter methodischer Zugänge –, wurde der Einsatz technischer Assistenz zur Förderung einer Teilnahme an Arbeit für Menschen mit geistiger Behinderung und hohem Unterstützunsgbedarf untersucht und unter Hinzunahme von zugehörigkeits-, arbeits- sowie anerkennungstheoretischer Perspektiven hinsichtlich der Institutionen(weiter)entwicklung von Werkstätten für behinderte Menschen betrachtet.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">A comprehensive realization of social participation for all individuals of the population presents itself as a specific challenge, in which the working world proves to be an important sphere.&#13;
In spite of normative reference points through socio-political innovations, particularly people with intellectual disabilities and a high need of support are excluded. Even in sheltered workshops, this group of people is excluded from participating in work as the challenges of life and labor in the 21st century are becoming ever more complex and the demands of the production and business side are growing to be stricter.&#13;
As a result, people with intellectual disabilities and a high need for support often fall off the radar in current inclusion efforts and – in spite of legal obligations – do not receive adequate support to participate in work.&#13;
In order to counteract the negligence and tacit acceptance of the deprivation of a large part of the sheltered workshop employees – in the sense of social affiliation by participation in work – design options for promoting a participation in work has to be considered comprehensively for them.&#13;
On the basis of an intensive field study and by using differentiated methodological approaches (mixed methods approach), the use of technical assistance to promote participation in work for people with intellectual disabilities and a high need for support was examined.&#13;
With the addition of perspectives on affiliation, work and recognition theory, the present work documents the promotion of participation in work through technical assistance for the group of people with intellectual disabilities and a high need for support as well as with regard to the (further) development of the institutions of sheltered workshops.&#13;
Following this, along with the characteristics of the phenomenon of promoting participation in work of people with intellectual disabilities and a high need for support, a critical reference is made to social contexts.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution>
         <cc:name>universi – Universitätsverlag Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Am Eichenhang 50, 57076 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dc:contributor xsi:type="pc:Contributor" thesis:role="referee">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Ulrike</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Buchmann</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:contributor>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2020-04-27</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2020</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-16830</dc:identifier>
   <dc:source xsi:type="ddb:ISBN">978-3-96182-072-6</dc:source>
   <dc:source xsi:type="ddb:noScheme">Siegen: universi – Universitätsverlag Siegen, 2020. - ISBN 978-3-96182-072-6</dc:source>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">ger</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät II (Bildung, Architektur, Künste)</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Baechler_Teilnahme an Arbeit durch Technische Assistenz_2020.pdf" ddb:fileSize="4874951"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">ee411f12cb14690e1923d5b5ea0035c2</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/1683/1/Baechler_Teilnahme%20an%20Arbeit%20durch%20Technische%20Assistenz_2020.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/1683</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>