<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>181</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Memetic algorithms for combinatorial optimization problems : fitness landscapes and effective search strategies</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Peter</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Merz</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">kombinatorische Optimierung</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">memetische Algorithmen</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Fitness-Landschaften</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">004</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">For many combinatorial optimization problems, no effective algorithms capable of finding guaranteed optimum solutions in short time are available. Therefore, powerful heuristics have been developed that deliver no guarantee to find the optimum, but have shown to be highly effective in many test cases. &#13;
In this work, a special class of heuristics is investigated. The algorithms under consideration are called memetic algorithms, which are – roughly speaking – hybrids of evolutionary algorithms and problem-specific search algorithms, such as greedy heuristics and local search. In order to provide explanations under which circumstances these memetic algorithms are highly effective, a search space analysis relying on the concept of fitness landscapes is conducted,&#13;
consisting of an autocorrelation analysis and a fitness distance correlation analysis of the peaks in the fitness landscape. It is shown that the former type of analysis enables a comparison and thus a selection of local search algorithms, while the latter type of analysis provides a guideline for the choice of evolutionary variation operators in the evolutionary meta-algorithm. &#13;
The search space analysis is conducted for five combinatorial optimization problems, namely the traveling salesman problem, the graph bipartitioning problem, the quadratic assignment problem, NK landscapes, and the unconstrained binary quadratic programming problem. Based on the results of the analysis, new memetic algorithms are presented. Experimental results demonstrate that they are among the best heuristics developed so far for the five problems.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Für viele kombinatorische Optimierungsprobleme sind keine effektiven Algorithmen bekannt, die garantiert optimale Lösungen in kurzer Zeit liefern. Daher sind leistungsfähige Heuristiken entwickelt worden, die zwar keine Garantie bieten, daß ein Optimum gefunden wird, sich aber in der Praxis als äußerst effektiv erwiesen haben. &#13;
In der vorliegenden Arbeit wird eine bestimmte Klasse von Heuristiken untersucht. Die betrachteten Algorithmen werden memetische Algorithmen genannt und können vereinfacht als hybride Verfahren aus evolutionären Algorithmen und problemspezifischen Heuristiken, wie Greedy-Heuristiken und lokale Suche aufgefaßt werden. Um erklären zu können, unter welchen Bedingungen diese memetischen Algorithmen effektiv sind, ist eine Suchraumanalyse basierend auf dem Konzept der Fitneßlandschaften durchgeführt worden, die aus einer Autokorrelationsanalyse und einer Fitneß-Distanz-Korrelationsanalyse der Gebirgsspitzen der Fitneßlandschaften besteht. Es wird gezeigt, daß die erstgenannte Analysemethode einen Vergleich und somit eine Auswahl von lokalen Suchverfahren erlaubt, wä;hrend die letztgenannte Analysemethode eine Richtlinie für die Wahl der Variationsoperatoren im evolutionären Meta-Algorithmus liefert. &#13;
Die Suchraumanalyse wurde auf fünf kombinatorische Optimierungsprobleme angewandt, dem Problem des Handlungsreisenden, dem Problem der Graph-Zerlegung, dem quadratischen Zuweisungsproblem, dem NK-Modell, und dem binären quadratischen Optimierungsproblem. Basierend auf den Analyseergebnissen wurden neue memetische Algorithmen entwickelt, und es wurde experimentell gezeigt, daß diese Algorithmen zu den besten bisher veröffentlichten Heuristiken für die fünf Probleme zählen.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2000-12-20</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2000</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-1816</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fachbereich 12, Elektrotechnik und Informatik</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>2</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="merz.pdf" ddb:fileSize="8196301"/>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="abst_ger.pdf" ddb:fileSize="22740"/>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/181</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>