<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>1927</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Praxisrelevante Sicherheitsforschung? Zur Bedeutung von Antizipationen in praxisorientierter Verbundforschung</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" ddb:type="translated" lang="eng">Practice-relevant security research? On the role of anticipations in practice-oriented collaborative research</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Tobias</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Dyrks</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Antizipation</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Antizipation</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Dialog</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Praxis</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Technik</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Innovation</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Anticipation</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Dialogue</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Practice</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Technology</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Innovation</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">620</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">Collaborative research between scientists from public research institutions with actors from civil society, such as practitioners, entrepreneurs, or domain-specific experts, has become ubiquitous in design-oriented research due to several reasons. On the one hand, applied-oriented research methodologies postulate the need for cooperation with practitioners during the evaluation of innovative artifacts in order to address stakeholder-relevant problems. On the other hand, as a precondition for funding of research proposals, both German and European funding policy demands on the involvement of entrepreneurs, end users or domain experts, to foster technical innovations with a sustainable potential for change in specific social domains.&#13;
Even though it pervades several areas of applied science disciplines, there is a fundamental lack of empirical knowledge to both inform and guide researchers on how the claim of cooperation can be concretely operationalized in research. How cooperative research processes constitute over time, and how early research phases of applied technology research can be managed adequately (phases such as problem definition and analysis, the exploration of alternative technical solutions in context of technical and practical feasibility), are not addressed by rather abstract research methodologies. Such recommendations would be very valuable to guide researchers in understanding, researching, and managing joint research projects.&#13;
In this dissertation an explorative study is presented that looks deeply into the collaboration work of a three years joint research project focused on developing an innovative navigation tool for reconnaissance missions of firefighters using ad-hoc deployable sensor-networks. The “Landmarke” project was one out of seven joint research projects of the so called “technology networks” of the Civil Security research programme, funded by the federal ministry of education and research of Germany between 2008 and 2011. The empirical interrogation of 60 hours of audio and video recordings provide access to the inner workings of project work among actors from a wide-range of professional backgrounds, such as scientists from several research institutions, firefighting practitioners and members of a firefighting training center; as well as entrepreneurs from different companies.&#13;
This study identifies by the case of Landmarke the role of anticipations in design-oriented research practice. Anticipations have an epistemological value in informing decisions in collaborative design and evaluation of technical artifacts. The epistemological value of anticipations is grounded in how well anticipations are informed by experience, and how anticipations are justified by intersubjective transparent assessments. &#13;
In the case of Landmarke, the reflections around firefighting practices to identify problems, and the introduction of technical artifacts to address navigation problems were closely intertwined. Collaborative reflections on navigation practice justified technical designs to support navigation. Collaborative evaluations of artefacts allowed firefighting practitioners to reflect navigation tactics on possible problems. This not only helped in moving forward the project, but also helped industry partners, scientists, and firefighters identifying the potential of the Landmarke technology as a promising tool way beyond supporting navigation.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Verbundkooperationen zwischen Wissenschaftlern öffentlicher Forschungseinrichtungen mit Akteuren der Zivilgesellschaft, wie Praktikern, Unternehmern oder Domänen-spezifischen Experten sind in der gestaltungsorientierten Forschung nahezu allgegenwärtig geworden. Einerseits postulieren Forschungsmethodologien den Bedarf zur Kooperation bei der Evaluation von innovativen Artefakten, um Bedürfnissen relevanter Anspruchsgruppen Rechnung zu tragen. Andererseits ist die Bereitschaft zur Verbundkooperation zur Förderbedingung in der europäischen und deutschen Förderpolitik erhoben worden, um praxistaugliche Technikinnovationen mit Potenzial für Wandel in spezifischen gesellschaftlichen Domänen zu fördern.&#13;
Trotz des hohen Stellenwerts von Forschungskooperationen dieser Art ist ein grundsätzlicher Mangel an empirischen Studien festzustellen. Wie sich kooperative Forschungsprozesse im Verlauf der Projektarbeit konstituieren, und wie Forschungsphasen der frühen der Technikentwicklung geeignet moderiert werden können, dazu fehlen jenseits abstrakter Grundsätze (z.B. zur Evaluation von technischen Artefakten im Forschungsprozess), die in Forschungs¬methodologien postuliert werden, konkretere Handreichungen für die Forschungs¬praxis. Solche Empfehlungen können wertvoll sein, um Forschern im Verständnis, bei der Erforschung und im Management von Verbundforschungsprojekten Handreichungen zu geben. &#13;
In dieser Dissertation wird eine explorative Studie vorgestellt, die Kooperationsarbeit in einem dreijährigen Verbundprojekt genauer untersucht, das auf die Entwicklung eines innovativen Navigationswerkzeugs für Erkundungseinsätze von Feuerwehrleuten unter Verwendung von ad hoc ausbringbaren Sensornetzwerken fokussiert gewesen ist. Das „Landmarke“-Projekt war ein von sieben Verbundforschungsprojekten, das vom deutschen Ministerium für Bildung und Forschung zwischen 2008 bis 2011 gefördert wurde. Die empirische Untersuchung von 60 Stunden Audio- und Videomaterials bietet Zugang zu inneren Abläufen von Verbundarbeit, an denen Akteure unterschiedlicher beruflicher Hintergründe beteiligt gewesen sind, wie Wissenschaftler verschiedener Forschungseinrichtungen, Praktiker und Ausbilder der Feuerwehr und Vertreter mehrerer Unternehmen. &#13;
Die Studie weist auf die Bedeutung von sog. Antizipationen für den gestaltungsorientierten Forschungsprozess hin, die einen erkenntnistheoretischen Wert bei Entscheidungen zur Gestaltung technischer Artefakte haben, wenn technische Artefakte am Nutzen für eine spezifische Praxis bewertet und verfeinert entwickelt werden. Der erkenntnistheoretische Wert von Antizipationen beruhte darauf, wie gut Antizipationen auf Erfahrungswerten basiert haben und inwiefern Antizipationen durch intersubjektive transparente Bewertungen gerechtfertigt waren. &#13;
Im Fall von Landmarke waren die Überlegungen zu Brandbekämpfungspraktiken zur Identifizierung von Problemen und die Einführung technischer Artefakte zur Behebung von Navigationsproblemen eng miteinander verknüpft. Gemeinsame Überlegungen der beteiligten Akteure zur Navigationspraxis rechtfertigten technische Entwürfe zur Unterstützung der Navigation. Durch gemeinsame Evaluationen von Artefakten konnten Feuerwehrleute die Navigationstaktiken zu möglichen Problemen reflektieren. Dies trug nicht nur dazu bei, das Projekt hinsichtlich einer technischen Weiterentwicklung voranzutreiben, sondern ermöglichte den Beteiligten, das Potenzial der Landmarke-Technologie als vielversprechendes Werkzeug zu identifizieren, das weit über den ursprünglichen Zweck „Unterstützung der Navigation von Feuerwehrleuten“ hinausging.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dc:contributor xsi:type="pc:Contributor" thesis:role="referee">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Volker</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Wulf</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:contributor>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2021-04-12</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2020</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-19278</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">ger</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät III - Wirtschaftswissenschaften, Wirtschaftsinformatik und Wirtschaftsrecht</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Dissertation_Tobias_Dyrks.pdf" ddb:fileSize="2198068"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">849efa50f7ce8f1e9ee595fb016e012e</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/1927/5/Dissertation_Tobias_Dyrks.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/1927</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>