<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>195</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Design, synthesis and studies of radical and radical ion probes : from enzyme investigations to electroactive surfactants</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Mukul</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Lal</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Coenzyme B 12</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Diol Dehydratase</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Pyrazinium tetrafluoroborate</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">540</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">The present work is centered at understanding the mechanistic details of the coenzyme B 12 dependent enzymes such as diol and glycerol dehydratase that are known to involve radical and radical ionic intermediates in transforming vicinal diols to carbonyl compounds. The work aims on translating such reactive intermediates to relatively long lived ones (making use of beta cleavage leading to persistent radical or electron transfer processes) thereby enabling their spectroscopic detection. A number of modified enzyme substrates attached with groups such as ferrocene, quinone and 2,2,6,6-tetramethylpiperidinoxy were synthesised and were investigated. The efficacies of electrophores to probe radical ions at the active site of the enzyme inherently rely on the electron transfer process. Modulation of the oxidising/reducing property of radical cation/radical anion formed at the active site invariably effects the trapping efficiency of the electrophore. Cyclic voltammetry investigations on the model compounds based on Fuson enols revealed that hydrogen bonding can indeed alter oxidation potentials of enols by up to 500 mV Fc cathodically. The concept was also tested in solution by generating and trapping radical cations in solution via inter as well as intramolecular electron transfer from ferrocene as a donor to enol/enol ether radical cation. Use of stable and reversible redox systems can set a precedent to the development of not only radical ion clocks, they can additionally prove pivotal in areas of nano-technology requiring transfer of small volumes (nano litre range) of solutes in a well defined manner. Thus a couple of redox active compounds were synthesised and investigated for their surfactant property, electrochemical and chemical stability.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Die vorliegende Arbeit beschäftigt sich mit mechanistischen Details der Coenzym B12-abhängigen Enzyme, z.B. Diol- und Glyceroldehydratase. Im Verlauf der Umwandlung vicinaler Diole in Carbonylverbindungen treten Radikale und Radikalionen als Zwischenstufen auf. Es wurde versucht diese reaktiven Zwischenstufen in langlebigere Modelle zu übersetzen, um so spektroskopische Untersuchungen zu ermöglichen. Dabei wurden ß-Spaltungs- und Elektronentransferreaktionen eingesetzt. Zahlreiche modifizierte Enzymsubstrate (mit zusätzlichen Ferrocen-, Chinon- und 2,2,6,6-Tetramethylpiperidinoxy-Substituenten) wurden synthetisiert und untersucht.. Die Wirksamkeit der Elektrophore bei der Untersuchung von Radikalionen im aktiven Zentrum des Enzyms hängt wesentlich vom Elektronentransferprozeß ab. Veränderungen der Oxidations-/Reduktionseigenschaften der gebildeten Radikalkationen/-anionen beeinflussen die Effizienz des Elektroneneinfangs der Elektrophore. CV-Messungen an Modellverbindungen, die auf Fuson Enolen basierten, zeigten, daß Wasserstoffbrückenbindungen die Oxidationspotentiale der Enole bis zu 500 mV Fc kathodisch verschieben. Dieses Konzept wurde auch in Lösung getestet, indem sowohl inter- als auch intramolekularer Elektronentransfer von Ferrocen zu Enol- bzw. Enolether-Radikalkationen untersucht wurde. Die Verwendung von stabilen reversiblen Redoxsystemen kann eine Schlüsselfunktion in der Nanotechnologie einnehmen, wenn es um den Transfer kleinster Flüssigkeitsvolumina (Nanoliter-Maßstab) geht. Daher wurden einige redoxaktive Verbindungen hergestellt und ihre Oberflächeneigenschaften sowie ihre elektrochemische und chemische Stabilität untersucht.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2005-01-20</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2004</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-1954</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fachbereich 8, Chemie - Biologie</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="lal.pdf" ddb:fileSize="11528640"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">674762d427cac458998bde578c93237c</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/195/1/lal.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/195</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>