<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>1970</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Universitäre Zwischenräume</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" ddb:type="translated" lang="eng">University in-between spaces: A contribution to the quantification and visualisation of structural-spatial synergy and adaptation potentials of university in-between spaces using the example of North Rhine-Westphalian campus universities of the 1970s</dc:title>
   <dcterms:alternative xsi:type="ddb:talternativeISO639-2" lang="ger">Ein Beitrag zur Quantiﬁzierung und Visualisierung baulich-räumlicher Synergie- und Anpassungspotentiale universitärer Zwischenräume am Beispiel nordrhein-westfälischer Campusuniversitäten der 1970er Jahre</dcterms:alternative>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Bartosz Józef</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Czempiel</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Campus</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Campus</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Universitäre Zwischenräume</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Architektur</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Städtebau</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Synergiepotential</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Anpassungspotential</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Zentrale Planungsstelle zur Rationalisierung von Landesbauten Nordrhein-Westfalen ZPL</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">campus</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">university in-between space</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">architecture</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">720</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Die physische Gestalt eines Campus (= lat. Feld) findet seine architektonische Ausformulierung im Begriff des Ensembles, welches ein räumlich-funktionales Zusammenspiel aus ‘Gebautem‘ und dem ‘dazwischen liegenden‘ Raum beschreibt. Dieses Zusammenspiel deutet sowohl auf die baulich-räumliche Synthese als auch auf die besondere Qualität des öffentlichen und halböffentlichen Raums im sozial-räumlichen Kontext hin.&#13;
Folglich kann demjenigen Raum eine besondere Bedeutung und Funktion beigemessen werden, der das bauliche Grundgerüst des (halb-)öffentlichen und privaten Raums bildet: Der universitäre Zwischenraum.&#13;
Die Zwischenräume sind auf allen Maßstabsebenen die verbindenden Elemente des universitären Gefüges. Sie formen das ‘räumliche Grundgerüst‘ und prägen gleichzeitig das ‘soziale Rückgrat‘. Sie bewirken Zusammenhalt und Trennung und sind die Garanten der privaten und der sozialen Sphäre. Die Zwischenräume sind folglich die entscheidenden Bindeglieder für die Belebung des Gemeinschaftlichen im ‘universitären Lebensraum‘.&#13;
Als Schnittstelle zwischen aktiven und passiven Handlungsmustern (Aktions- und Rückzugsräume) können die Zwischenräume - zeitlich versetzt oder gar gleichzeitig - als Orte der Kommunikation oder der Kontemplation, des Lehrens oder des Lernens, des Verweilens oder des Beobachtens fungieren. In ihrer ‘informellen‘ Funktion sind die Zwischenräume also vielschichtig und konträr zugleich. Gerade dieses Funktionsspektrum ist für eine kreative und innovative Wissensgesellschaft von großer Bedeutung, denn „der moderne wie der alte Weg des Wissenstransfers“ erschöpft sich nicht nur auf reiner Informationsvermittlung (Sprechen und Hören), sondern vielmehr auf der Kommunikation (Sprechen, Darstellen, Hören und Sehen). Aus diesem Grund können die Zwischenräume als „Indikatoren und als Promotoren universitärer Kultur“ betrachtet werden.&#13;
Die vorliegende Untersuchung bewegt sich im Campus-Zwischenraum, um im ‘kleinen‘, menschlichen Maßstab die Synergie- und Anpassungspotentiale der baulichen Strukturen im Bestand zu untersuchen. In diesem Zusammenhang rücken die in der Umgangssprache oftmals als ‘Zweckbauten‘ deklarierten Campusgebäude der ehemaligen Gesamthochschulen an den Standorten in Essen, Paderborn und Wuppertal in den Vordergrund der Untersuchung. &#13;
Zur quantitativen Ermittlung der Synergie- und Anpassungspotentiale von universitären Zwischenräumen wurde im Rahmen dieser Arbeit eine neue Methodik entwickelt, die auf der Konfigurationstheorie nach Hillier und Hanson (The Social Logic of Space, 1984) aufbaut und einem holistischen Ansatz folgend quantitative Bewertungen für die untersuchten Raumabschnitte liefert und damit auch eine Vergleichbarkeit zwischen verschiedenen Räumen und Standorten ermöglicht.&#13;
Zunächst wurde durch die Entflechtung der einzelnen Strukturelemente die Lagegunst der zu untersuchenden Raumabschnitte in den jeweiligen Campusstandorten ermittelt. Da die direkten, wahrnehmbaren Wirkungs- und Beziehungsqualitäten in der Raumsyntax-Analyse (Hillier und Hanson) nicht enthalten sind, wurden im zweiten Schritt der Analyse die abstrakten, konfigurativen Parameter der Campusstrukturen (Raumsyntax) um die konkreten Parameter der Raumabschnitte (Gestalt, Funktion und Verbindung) ergänzt.  &#13;
Anschließend wurden die Anpassungspotentiale beleuchtet. Dazu werden für jeden Standort ausgewählte Raumabschnitte im Einzelnen auf ihr Optimierungspotential untersucht. Dabei werden die Parameter Gestalt, Funktion und Verbindung für die Bestimmung des Synergiepotentials zugrunde gelegt. Aus der folgenden Bestimmung des Anpassungspotentials durch Umnutzung, Umbau und Erweiterung kann die praktische Realisierbarkeit dieser Synergiepotentiale abgeleitet werden.&#13;
Auf Basis der Raumkategorie des Zwischenraums werden schlussendlich Handlungsempfehlungen zur Sanierung der untersuchten Campusanlagen aufgezeigt, aber auch Grenzen der Optimierung erläutert, die durch den Bestand gegeben sind.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">The physical form of a campus (= lat. field) finds its architectural formulation in the concept of the ensemble, which describes a spatial-functional interaction of the 'built' and the 'intervening' space. This interaction indicates both the structural-spatial synthesis and the special quality of public and semi-public space in the socio-spatial context.&#13;
Consequently, special significance and function can be attributed to the space that forms the basic structural framework of (semi-)public and private space: The university interstitial space.&#13;
The interstitial spaces are the connecting elements of the university structure at all scales. They form the 'spatial framework' and at the same time shape the 'social backbone'. They bring about cohesion and separation and are the guarantors of the private and social spheres. Consequently, the interstitial spaces are the crucial links for animating the communal life in the 'university living space'.&#13;
As an interface between active and passive patterns of action (action and retreat spaces), the in-between spaces can function - temporally staggered or even simultaneously - as places of communication or contemplation, of teaching or learning, of lingering or observing. In their 'informal' function, the in-between spaces are thus multi-layered and contrary at the same time. It is precisely this functional spectrum that is of great importance for a creative and innovative knowledge society, because "the modern as well as the traditional way of knowledge transfer" is not exhausted on pure information transfer (speaking and listening), but rather on communication (speaking, presenting, listening and seeing). For this reason, the in-between spaces can be considered as "indicators and as promoters of university culture".&#13;
The present study focusses on the campus in-between spaces in order to investigate, on a 'small', human scale, the synergy and adaption potentials in the existing environment. In this context, the campus buildings of the former comprehensive universities at the locations in Essen, Paderborn and Wuppertal, often declared in colloquial language as 'functional buildings', move into the focus of the investigation.&#13;
For the quantitative determination of the synergy and adaption potentials of the university in-between spaces within the scope of this work a new methodology based on the configuration theory according Hillier and Hanson (The Social Logic of Space, 1984) has been developed, which following a holistic approach provides quantified assesssments for the examined spatial sections and therefore enables comparability between different spaces and locations.   &#13;
First, by disentangling the individual structural elements, the locational favourability of the spatial sections under investigation was determined in the respective campus locations. Since the direct, perceptible impact and relationship qualities are not included in the spatial syntax analysis (by Hillier and Hanson), the abstract, configurative parameters of the campus structures (spatial syntax) were supplemented by the concrete parameters of the spatial sections (shape, function and connection) in the second step of the analysis.  &#13;
Subsequently, the adaptation potentials were illuminated. For this purpose, selected spatial sections for each location are examined in detail for their optimisation potential. The parameters shape, function and connection are used as a basis for determining the synergy potential. The practical feasibility of these synergy potentials can be derived from the following determination of the adaptation potential through conversion, remodelling and expansion.&#13;
Finally, on the basis of the spatial category of the in-between space, recommendations for action for the redevelopment of the studied campuses are pointed out, but also limits to optimisation are explained, which are given by the existing situation.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dc:contributor xsi:type="pc:Contributor" thesis:role="referee">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Peter</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Karle</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:contributor>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2021-07-27</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2021</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-19702</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">ger</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Department Architektur</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Dissertation_Bartosz Czempiel.pdf" ddb:fileSize="263891008"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">8901cd0547c7991dfe7c6898bf0b6e69</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/1970/4/Dissertation_Bartosz%20Czempiel.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/1970</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>