<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>1983</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Identification and analysis of transporters involved in the elimination of insecticidal compounds from the red flour beetle, Tribolium castaneum</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" ddb:type="translated" lang="ger">Identifizierung und Analyse von Transportern, die an der Eliminierung von insektiziden Verbindungen durch den rotbraunen Reismehlkäfer, Tribolium castaneum, beteiligt sind</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Janin</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Rösner</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Tribolium castaneum</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Insecticide</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Resistance</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">physiology</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">590</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">Most insects are beneficial creatures, but among them are many pests that can pose a risk to human nutrition and health. Because of this, insects are need to be controlled, which can be achieved by various classes of insecticides. Due to the fact that insecticide resistance is increasing worldwide, a profound knowledge on the underlying mechanisms of insecticide resistance becomes more and more important. One way to eliminate insecticide from the insect body involves integral transmembrane proteins such as ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transporters, which mediate the ATP-dependent translocation of a variety of substrates across cell membranes, including xenobiotics. While ABC transporters have been extensively analysed in bacteria and vertebrates, little is known about their physiological functions in insects. A previous study of ABC transporters in the red flour beetle, Tribolium castaneum, revealed that the genome of this beetle harbours more than 70 ABC transporter encoding genes. Those can be grouped into eight known insect subfamilies namely ABCA to ABCH. The ABCB and ABCC subfamilies contain P-glycoproteins (P-gp or MDR) and multidrug resistance proteins (MRP) that are discussed to contribute to insecticide elimination. Other transport proteins include the organic anion transporting polypeptides (OATPs), which also transport a large variety of substrates across cell membranes. Some of them are expressed together with ABC transporters or other detoxification enzymes in the same tissues, and hence may play an important role in the transport of insecticides and/or their metabolites. T. castaneum is a well-established genetic pest model, allowing the analysis of gene functions in the development of insecticide resistances. To identify transporters involved in insecticide elimination, three methods were used in this study: (1) gene expression analyses, (2) a competitive fluorescence-based elimination assay and (3) ABC and OATP inhibitors. Different TcABC and TcOATP genes were found to be upregulated in excretory tissues and insecticide-treated larvae. RNA interference (RNAi) was used to analyse the influence of ABC transporters and OATPs and the knockdown of specific ABC and OATP genes resulted in a significant increase in mortality of insects that were treated with different insecticides. Moreover, RNAi knockdowns of some specific ABC and OATP genes led to mortality even in the absence of any insecticide. Their phenotypes resemble other genes known to be involved in the hormonal control of ecdysteroids indicating essential physiological functions during molting. In summary, the data presented in this study show that ABC transporters and OATPs are involved in the elimination of insecticides and in the transport of ecdysteroids.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Die meisten Insekten sind Nützlinge. Viele sind jedoch Schädlinge, die eine Gefahr für die menschliche Ernährung und Gesundheit darstellen können. Diese Schädlinge können durch verschiedene Klassen von Insektiziden bekämpft werden. Aufgrund der Tatsache, dass Resistenzen gegenüber Insektiziden weltweit zunehmen, wird ein fundiertes Wissen über die zugrundeliegenden Mechanismen der Insektizidresistenz immer wichtiger. Eine Möglichkeit, Insektizide aus dem Insektenkörper zu eliminieren, sind Transportproteine wie ABC Transporter (englisch: ATP binding cassette, ABC) oder organische Anionen transportierende Polypeptide (OATPs), welche die Translokation einer Vielzahl von Substraten über Zellmembranen vermitteln. Einige OATPs werden zusammen mit ABC-Transportern und anderen Entgiftungsenzymen in denselben Geweben exprimiert und könnten daher ebenfalls eine wichtige Rolle beim Transport von Insektiziden oder deren Metaboliten spielen. &#13;
Tribolium castaneum, der Rotbraune Reismehlkäfer, ist ein gut etabliertes genetisches Schädlingsmodell, dass die Analyse von Genfunktionen bei der Entwicklung von Insektizidresistenzen ermöglicht. Zur Identifizierung von Transportern, die an der Insektizid-Eliminierung beteiligt sind, wurden in dieser Arbeit neben der Durchführung von Genexpressionsanalysen, ein kompetitiver Fluoreszenz-basierter Eliminationsassay etabliert und ABC- und OATP-Inhibitoren eingesetzt. Es wurde festgestellt, dass verschiedene ABC- und OATP-Gene in Ausscheidungsgeweben und mit Insektiziden behandelten Larven hochreguliert sind. Um den Einfluss der ABC-Transporter und OATPs zu analysieren, wurde RNA-Interferenz (RNAi) eingesetzt. Der Knockdown spezifischer TcABC- und TcOATP-Gene führte zu einer signifikanten Erhöhung der Mortalität von Insekten, die mit verschiedenen Insektiziden behandelt wurden. Darüber hinaus führte der Knockdown einiger spezifischer ABC- und OATP-Gene zu einer Mortalität in Abwesenheit jeglicher Insektizide. Hierbei entstanden Phänotypen, die anderen Genen ähneln, von denen bekannt ist, dass sie an der hormonellen Kontrolle von Ecdysteroiden beteiligt sind, was auf essentielle physiologische Funktionen während der Häutung hinweist. &#13;
Zusammenfassend zeigen die in dieser Studie vorgestellten Daten, dass ABC-Transporter und OATPs an der Eliminierung von Insektiziden und an dem Transport von Ecdysteroiden beteiligt sind.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dc:contributor xsi:type="pc:Contributor" thesis:role="referee">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Hans</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Merzendorfer</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:contributor>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2021-08-03</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2021</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-19835</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Institut für Biologie</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Dissertation_Janin_Roesner.pdf" ddb:fileSize="5045533"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">5488c2a3812704b052dfe6414f4dc45b</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/1983/5/Dissertation_Janin_Roesner.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/1983</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>