<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>2105</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Lightweight concept design of economical FRTP-metal multi-material vehicle doors</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" ddb:type="translated" lang="ger">Leichtbaukonzept für wirtschaftliche FRTP-Metall Multimaterial-Fahrzeugtüren</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Danshi</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Li</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Leichtbau</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Vehicle door</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Lightweight design</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Multi-material construction</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Fiber-reinforced thermoplastics</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Fahrzeugtür</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Leichtbau</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Multi-Material-Bauweise</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Faserverstärkte Thermoplaste</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">620</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">The vehicle door, as a major steel-intensive closure, can achieve a certain degree of weight-saving potential by the use of lightweight materials and new design principles. Due to the different stiffness and strength requirements on different areas of vehicle doors under static and crash loading conditions, multi-material construction can be one of the most effective ways to achieve lightweight design with minimal additional cost. This work illustrates an approach for the design of economical lightweight multi-material vehicle door concepts based on a market-available steel reference, while considering typical static and crash loading cases. An innovative door structure is introduced that includes a major load-bearing ring structure and a highly function-integrated inner panel. The structure incorporates economical lightweight materials, such as aluminum, long-fiber thermoplastics, and unidirectional tapes, and corresponding mass-production-oriented manufacturing methods. Anisotropy analysis under different loadings guarantees an effective use of unidirectional tapes. Topology and parameter optimizations provide design suggestions for rib structures of long-fiber-reinforced thermoplastics. The final door concepts achieve ca. 20% weight reduction and comparable mechanical performance compared to the steel reference door. Especially for the crash loading case, an innovative component development method is used to validate the final door concepts, which rebuilds the crash behavior close to the full-vehicle scenario with limited surrounding components.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Die Fahrzeugtür als große stahlintensive Klappe kann durch den Einsatz von Leichtbaumaterialien und neuen Konstruktionsprinzipien ein gewisses Gewichtseinsparpotenzial erzielen. Aufgrund der unterschiedlichen Steifigkeits- und Festigkeitsanforderungen an unterschiedliche Bereiche von Fahrzeugtüren unter statischen und Crash-Lastfällen kann die Multi-Material-Konstruktion eine der effektivsten Möglichkeiten sein, Leichtbau mit minimalen Zusatzkosten zu erreichen. Diese Arbeit zeigt einen Gestaltungsansatz von wirtschaftlichen Leichtbau-Multimaterial-Fahrzeugtürkonzepten auf Basis einer marktverfügbaren Stahlreferenz unter Berücksichtigung typischer statischer und Crash-Lastfälle. Es wird eine innovative Türstruktur vorgestellt, die eine tragende Ringstruktur und ein hochfunktionsintegriertes Innenblech umfasst. In der Struktur werden wirtschaftliche Leichtbaumaterialien wie Aluminium, langfaserverstärkte Thermoplaste und unidirektionale Tapes sowie entsprechende massenproduktionsorientierte Fertigungsmethoden eingesetzt. Die Anisotropieanalyse unter verschiedenen Belastungen garantiert einen effektiven Einsatz von unidirektionalen Tapes. Topologie- und Parameteroptimierungen liefern Designvorschläge für Rippenstrukturen aus langfaserverstärkten Thermoplasten. Die finalen Türkonzepte erreichen ca. 20% Gewichtsreduzierung und eine vergleichbare mechanische Leistung im Vergleich zur Stahlreferenztür. Speziell für den Crash-Lastfall wird zur Validierung der finalen Türkonzepte eine innovative Komponentenentwicklungsmethode eingesetzt, die das Crashverhalten nahe am Gesamtfahrzeugszenario mit begrenzten Umgebungskomponenten nachbildet.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution>
         <cc:name>universi – Universitätsverlag Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Am Eichenhang 50, 57076 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dc:contributor xsi:type="pc:Contributor" thesis:role="referee">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Xiangfan</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Fang</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:contributor>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2021-11-02</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2021</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-21057</dc:identifier>
   <dc:source xsi:type="ddb:ISBN">978-3-96182-113-6</dc:source>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dcterms:isPartOf xsi:type="ddb:noScheme">Siegener Schriftenreihe Automobiltechnik;  8</dcterms:isPartOf>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Institut für Fahrzeugtechnik</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="FLB_8_Dissertation_Li.pdf" ddb:fileSize="16219801"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">60b722b4e3e419d776e3c2d828b55245</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/2105/3/FLB_8_Dissertation_Li.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/2105</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>