<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>228</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Product engineering for silicon based MEMS IP</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Dirk</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Ortloff</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Microsystems</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Intellectual Property</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Semiconductor IP</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">004</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">Today the silicon based Micro Electro-Mechanical Systems (MEMS) industry&#13;
has inadequate development methodologies and frameworks. This is especially&#13;
true when developing MEMS process and design Intellectual Property&#13;
(IP). The existing development methods and frameworks are not accommodating&#13;
for the necessary areas and components required for efficient, reproducible&#13;
and controlled MEMS IP development. As such issues have not been&#13;
addressed, this results in e.g. unresolved development methodology questions&#13;
and non-systematic storage of product deliverables.&#13;
&#13;
This thesis proposes a systematic development approach to tackle several&#13;
of such insufficiencies. It proposes a novel MEMS IP development methodology&#13;
guiding the developments from a product idea to a marketable product.&#13;
Because the business processes of the method require tool support, a quality&#13;
integrated Product Engineering Framework is proposed supporting the key areas.&#13;
The thesis describes a new framework concept of business process components&#13;
supporting the methodology and establishes processes guiding through&#13;
the development efforts.&#13;
&#13;
A major focus is set on the in-depth research of reproducibility and control&#13;
aspects of the process IP development efforts. The findings concerning process&#13;
development tracking are converted into novel concepts for supporting tools&#13;
and the newly implemented software environment to address the found problem&#13;
areas is introduced. The thesis presents results generated during the EU&#13;
FP6 project PROMENADE [Eur04] and previous works. The software environment&#13;
developed by the PROMENADE project builds a major cornerstone of a&#13;
company wide framework for developing silicon based MEMS IP modules.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Die Industrie für siliziumbasierte Mikrosysteme hat heute keine adäquaten&#13;
Entwicklungsmethoden und -umgebungen. Dies gilt speziell für Firmen,&#13;
die ein wissensbasiertes Geschäftsmodell (Intellectual Property, IP) verfolgen.&#13;
Die existierenden Methoden und Umgebungen unterstützen nicht alle&#13;
erforderlichen Bereiche und bieten nicht alle notwendigen Komponenten&#13;
für die Mikrosystementwicklung. Diese unzureichende Unterstützung führt,&#13;
unter anderem, zu unvollständigen und nicht reproduzierbaren Entwicklungsflüssen. Dies ist vor allem auf die unsystematische Speicherung der&#13;
Entwicklungs- und Produktergebnissen zurückzuführen.&#13;
&#13;
Diese Doktorarbeit stellt einen systematischen Entwicklungsansatz vor, der&#13;
mehrere dieser Probleme bearbeitet. Hierzu werden alle relevanten Aspekte&#13;
analysiert und exemplarische Lösungsvorschläge aufgezeigt. Es wird eine neue Methodik bereitgestellt, welche von der Idee bis zum vermarktbaren,&#13;
wissensbasierten Mikrosystemprodukt führt. Hierzu wird eine Umgebung&#13;
aus Geschäftsprozessen und Unterstützungswerkzeugen für die Methodik beschrieben.&#13;
&#13;
Ein besonderes Augenmerk wird auf die detaillierte Analyse von&#13;
Reproduzierbarkeits- und Kontrollaspekten der Fertigungsprozessentwicklung&#13;
gelegt. Die Ergebnisse wurden zur Entwicklung neuer Konzepte und&#13;
Werkzeuge zur Entwicklungsunterstützung in der Praxis eingesetzt. Die Arbeit&#13;
präsentiert Ergebnisse aus dem von der EU geförderten Projekt PROMENADE&#13;
[Eur04] und des Vorläuferprototypen PDTS. Die innerhalb des Projektes&#13;
entwickelte Softwareumgebung bildet einen Grundpfeiler für die firmenweite&#13;
eingesetzte Entwicklungsumgebung.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2006-06-25</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2006</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-2287</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fachbereich 12, Elektrotechnik und Informatik</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="ortloff.pdf" ddb:fileSize="14016023"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">bb5fa41c1059e5163c05ac4da014c991</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/228/1/ortloff.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/228</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>