<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>281</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Nominal and real rigidities in monetary stochastic dynamic general equilibrium models of the business cycle</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Nominale und reale Rigiditäten in monetären dynamischen stochastischen allgemeinen Gleichgewichtsmodellen des Konjunkturzyklus</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Michael</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Gail</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Realer-Konjunkturzyklus-Theorie</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">rigide Preise</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">optimale Geldpolitik</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Neue Neoklassische Synthese</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Persistenz</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">monetärer Transmissionsprozess</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">New Neoclassical Synthesis</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Sticky Prices</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Monetary Transmission Mechanism</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Persistence</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Sticky Wages</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">330</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">The purpose of the present study is to explore the specific contributions of various&#13;
nominal and real rigidities in monetary DGE models in a systematic way and in&#13;
a common framework. I will concentrate on a quite simple model setup in order&#13;
to find out the important transmission mechanisms at work. The focus will be on&#13;
exogenous money growth shocks as the driving force of the business cycle and not&#13;
on interest rate shocks. The book contains five main chapters. All these chapters are presented in a way&#13;
that allows the reader to study them separately. Therefore the building blocks of&#13;
the models will be repeated in every chapter. The first four chapters are concerned&#13;
with the question which rigidities are essential to explain actual business cycles while&#13;
Chapter 6 analyzes optimal monetary policy in a stochastic DGE model.&#13;
In Chapter 2 the basic model is presented. Prices are set in a staggered way&#13;
as in Taylor (1980). The chapter addresses two questions that have not yet been&#13;
answered in the literature. First: Is there a difference between money introduced&#13;
via a CIA-constraint or via a MIU-specification? Second: Does it matter how the&#13;
household’s preferences look like? The answers are yes in both cases. It turns out&#13;
that the CIA-model with a standard CRRA utility function can better account for&#13;
the business cycle. Thus in Chapter 3 the MIU-setup as well as GHH preferences&#13;
will be discarded. But the model will be augmented by capital accumulation considerations.&#13;
The chapter considers instead the implications of the price setting scheme:&#13;
Taylor pricing is compared to Calvo pricing. It turns out that the failure of the basic&#13;
model to generate persistent output responses is due to Taylor type price staggering.&#13;
The model version with Calvo pricing can account quite well for the empirical&#13;
impulse responses, confirming the results of Kiley (2002) in a more general setup.&#13;
Chapter 4 considers the role of habits in consumption. While this feature has&#13;
already been analyzed by others, e.g. Christiano, Eichenbaum and Evans (2003),&#13;
there is no study that tries to figure out the specific effects of habit formation in&#13;
isolation. In addition, related studies use Calvo pricing. Here the MIU-model with&#13;
Taylor price staggering will again be considered in order to examine whether this&#13;
can improve the model with respect to its ability to create persistence in output.&#13;
Unfortunately only the response of consumption to a money growth shock can be&#13;
improved. For a high enough value of the habit persistence parameter consumption&#13;
can even be hump-shaped, as it is empirically (see Figure 1.4).&#13;
Chapter 5 presents a model with Taylor wage staggering and adjustment costs&#13;
of price changes as in Rotemberg (1982). It turns out that this specific combination&#13;
is important to get persistent output responses to a money growth shock. When&#13;
using also Taylor price staggering the result breaks down and output and prices will&#13;
not be persistent. Sticky prices through adjustment costs of prices operate similar&#13;
as sticky prices under Calvo pricing. When they interact with adjustment costs of&#13;
capital they can even strengthen the persistence in output. In the absence of the&#13;
costs for adjusting the capital stock there are only very moderate effects on output.&#13;
Chapter 6 goes a step further. Here the question is not whether a monetary&#13;
stochastic DGE model can generate persistence but whether a central bank can&#13;
stabilize the price level as claimed by King and Wolman (1999). The analysis builds&#13;
upon the framework used before: the household maximizes life-time utility and firms&#13;
maximize profits. The central bank acts as a social planner that takes into account&#13;
the optimizing behavior of the household and the firms. Maximizing welfare is then&#13;
equivalent to maximizing utility of the representative household. It is shown that&#13;
the result of King and Wolman does not hold under a different specification of the&#13;
preference function so that in general the monetary authority will not be successful&#13;
in completely stabilizing the price level, as is also observed empirically. Chapter 7 summarizes the main findings and gives some suggestions for future research while Chapter 1 discusses briefly important advances in macroeconomic theory as well as in empirical methods to characterize the business cycle.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2004-10-26</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2004</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-2814</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.habilitation</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fachbereich 5, Wirtschaftswissenschaften, Wirtschaftsinformatik und Wirtschaftsrecht</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Gail_Habilitationsschrift.pdf" ddb:fileSize="1304974"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">fbf479a52124cd74b18514c002b6f5b0</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/281/1/Gail_Habilitationsschrift.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/281</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>