<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>45</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Development of a low noise analog readout for a DEPFET pixel detector</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Entwicklung einer rauscharmen analogen Auslese für einen DEPFET-Pixeldetektor</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Adrian Sorin</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Niculae</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">DEPFET</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">DEPFET</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">low-noise</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">regulated cascade</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">530</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">Silicon pixel detectors have become very popular in a large variety of applications such as experimental particle physics, medical imaging, video and digital cameras. The DEPFET pixel detector is a novel concept of a silicon detector consisting of a JFET transistor integrated on a fully depleted silicon substrate. The signal charge generated by an ionizing particle within the detector substrate is collected at the transistor gate by means of a special depletion scheme called sideward depletion. From the gate, the signal charge modulates directly the JFET channel current. The current signal is further ampliﬁed and processed by external electronics. The internal ampliﬁcation mechanism ensures low noise, even at room temperature. The electrical charge is removed from the JFET gate by a clear mechanism. Two possible clear methods have been suggested: pulsed clear and continuous clear. In the present work, DEPFET structures with continuous clear mechanism have been studied. A low noise analog readout circuit has been developed in CMOS technology. This readout chip has been tested with diﬀerent DEPFET pixel structures. By recording energy spectra of known radioactive sources, an electronic noise of about 13 e− has been measured at room temperature. The DEPFET device opens therefore new possibilities for applications that require very good energy resolution at room temperature.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Silizium Pixel-Detektoren werden in vielen Bereichen eingesetzt, zum Beispiel&#13;
in der experimentellen Teilchenphysik, bei bildgebenden Verfahren in der&#13;
Medizin oder in Video- und Digitalkameras. Der DEPFET-Pixel-Detektor&#13;
beruht auf einen neuen Konzept für Silizium Detektoren. Er besteht aus&#13;
einem JFET-Transistor, welcher auf einem vollständig verarmten Silizium&#13;
Substrat integriert ist. Eine durch ionisierende Partikel hervorgerufene&#13;
Ladung wird am Gate des Transistors mittels sogenannter ”Seitwärtsverarmung”&#13;
gesammelt. Diese Ladung moduliert direkt den JFET-Kanalstrom,&#13;
welcher dann in einer externen Schaltung verstärkt und weiterverarbeitet&#13;
wird. Der interne Verstärkungsmechanismus garantiert selbst bei Raumtemperatur&#13;
ein geringes Rauschen. Die am Gate des JFET entstandene Ladung&#13;
wird durch einen Löschmechanismus entfernt. Dafür wurden zwei Methoden&#13;
vorgeschlagen: gepulster und kontinuierlicher Löschmechanismus.&#13;
In der hier vorliegenden Arbeit werden DEPFET-Detektoren mit kontinuierlichem&#13;
Löschmechanismus untersucht. Eine rauscharme analoge Ausleseelektronik&#13;
wurde mittels CMOS-Technologie entwickelt und an verschiedenen&#13;
DEPFET-Pixelstrukturen getestet. Durch Aufnahme von Energiespektren&#13;
bekannter radioaktive Quellen, konnte ein Rauschen von ungefähr 13&#13;
Elektronen bei Raumtemperatur gemessen werden. Der DEPFET eröffnet&#13;
daher neue Möglichkeiten für Anwendungen bei denen es auf gute Energieauflösung bei Raumtemperatur ankommt.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2004-01-22</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2004</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-459</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fachbereich 7, Physik</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="niculae.pdf" ddb:fileSize="4091759"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">8e63127dc6dfa661df2f7fa5a7b33bb1</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/45/1/niculae.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/45</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>