<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>674</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Prominence assignment in English triconstituent compounds</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Die Betonung dreigliedriger Komposita im Englischen</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Kristina</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Kösling</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Verzweigungsrichtung</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Variation</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Tonhöhe</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">branching direction</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Lexical Category Prominence Rule</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">prominence variation</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">pitch</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">stress</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">420</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">It has been argued that prominence assignment in triconstituent compounds depends on the compound's branching direction. Left-branching compounds (e.g. [seat belt] law) have highest prominence on the leftmost constituent, whereas right-branching compounds have highest prominence on the second constituent of the entire compound (e.g. [team [locker room]). This assumption is captured, for instance, in Liberman and Prince's (1977) 'Lexical Category Prominence Rule'. A closer look at the relevant literature reveals, however, that this generalization is not the result of large-scale empirical investigations. Instead, the generalization seems to be based on the analysis of small sets of self-selected, mostly isolated examples. In addition, the assignment of prominence to triconstituent compounds has been primarily based on the researchers' own intuition about prominence (e.g. Kingdon 1958; Liberman and Prince1977; Giegerich 1985; Giegerich 1992; Carstairs-McCarthy 2002; Berg 2009). However, this approach to determine prominence in compounds has been argued to be problematic since speakers may vary in their assignment of prominence to one and the same compound (e.g. Bauer 1983a; Plag 2006; Kunter 2011). Last but not least, the LCPR is based on the assumption that Noun+Noun (NN) compounds in English are categorically left prominent (e.g. séat belt; lócker room). Yet, recent experimental and corpus studies (e.g Plag 2006, Lappe and Plag 2007, Plag et al 2008, Plag and Kunter 2010 and Kunter 2011) dealing with prominence assignment in biconstituent compounds have shown that a considerable number of right prominent NN compounds exist in English as well. Given this variable prominence behaviour of NN compounds, which function as complex constituents in triconstituent compounds, we have good reasons to assume that right prominent NN compounds also affect prominence assignment in Noun+Noun+Noun compounds (NNN).&#13;
The thesis presents a systematic investigation of the prominence behaviour of English triconstituent NNN compounds analyzing both large amounts of speech corpus data and experimentally obtained data. On the one hand, it addresses the question to what extent the LCPR actually holds for left- and right-branching compounds. On the other hand, it presents the first study that empirically investigates whether the existence of right prominent NN compounds affects prominence assignment in triconstituent NNN compounds. In addition to that, the present thesis differs from previous accounts dealing with prominence assignment in triconstituent compounds regarding the methodology applied to account for the prominence behaviour of NNN compounds; acoustic measurements of pitch are used to determine the prominence patterns of such compounds rather than relying on a few individual speaker judgments.&#13;
The thesis shows that the LCPR is wrong and that a considerable number of violations to the rule exist. Furthermore it is shown that the existence of right prominent NN compounds needs to be incorporated in any account that tries to explain prominence assignment in triconstituent compounds. Right prominent NNs occur embedded in triconstituent compounds and they may cause the right member of the complex constituent to be the highest prominent one of the compound, contra the LCPR.  Finally, the thesis provides evidence that analogy, a factor found to be responsible for prominence variation in NN compounds, also plays a role in prominence assignment to triconstituent compounds.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Im Hinblick auf die Betonung dreigliedriger Komposita geht man bislang davon aus, dass diese von der jeweiligen Verzweigungsrichtung des Kompositums abhängt. So wird angenommen das linksverzweigte Komposita (z.B [seat belt] law) auf der insgesamt ersten Konstituente betont sind, rechtsverzweigte Komposita (z.B. team [locker room]) hingegen auf der zweiten Konstituente des gesamten Kompositums. Diese Generalisierung zur Betonung dreigliedriger Komposita ist unter anderem in der von Liberman und Prince (1977) formulierten Lexical Category Prominence Rule (LCPR) festgehalten. &#13;
Die LCPR erscheint jedoch aus mehreren Gründen äußerst fragwürdig. So gibt es bislang, abgesehen von einigen wenigen, kleineren Studien (e.g. Kingdon1958; Kvam 1990; Berg 2009 und Giegerich 2009), keine empirischen Untersuchungen, die die Vorhersagen der LCPR systematisch überprüft haben. Stattdessen scheinen die Generalisierungen zur Betonung dreigliedriger Komposita ausschließlich auf der Analyse vereinzelter Beispiele zu beruhen. Darüber hinaus basiert die Zuweisung der Betonung zu diesen rechts- und linksverzweigten Komposita überwiegend auf der subjektiven Wahrnehmung der jeweiligen Wissenschaftler. Diese subjektive Methode zur Bestimmung der Betonung ist allerdings problematisch, wie Studien von z. B Bauer (1983), Plag (2006) und Kunter (2011) gezeigt haben. Demnach scheinen sich Sprecher oftmals uneinig darüber zu sein, wie ein Kompositum betont wird, wodurch es zu Variation in den Urteilen kommen kann. Ein weiteres Problem der LCPR ist, dass diese auf der Annahme beruht, dass Komposita im Englischen kategorisch links betont sind, wodurch sie sich von syntaktischen Phrasen unterscheiden, die generell rechts betont sind. In der Literatur findet man aber nicht nur links betonte NN Komposita, sondern auch eine Vielzahl an rechts betonten NN Komposita (e.g. Fudge 1984; Liberman and Sproat1992; Plag 2006; Plag et al. 2007; Plag et al. 2008; Plag 2010 und Kunter 2011). Da diese Komposita, wie bereits erwähnt, nicht in der Vorhersage der LCPR berücksichtigt werden, muss deren Existenz auch Konsequenzen für die LCPR haben.&#13;
In der vorliegenden Arbeit wird, mithilfe akustischer Messungen der Tonhöhe, das Betonungsverhalten dreigliedriger Komposita genauer betrachtet.  In einer Korpusstudie wird die Frage untersucht, inwieweit die LCPR überhaupt die richtigen Vorhersagen macht. In zwei Produktionsexperimenten wird zum aller ersten Mal explizit der mögliche Einfluss zweigliedriger rechts betonter Komposita auf die Betonung dreigliedriger Komposita untersucht. &#13;
Die Arbeit zeigt, dass die LCPR falsch ist und die Existenz rechts betonter NN Komposita einen Einfluss auf die Betonung dreigliedriger Komposita hat. Rechts betonte NN Komposita kommen zum Beispiel als komplexes Glied in dreigliedrigen Komposita vor, wodurch diese Komposita nicht auf dem linken, sondern dem rechten Glied der komplexen Konstituente betont sein können. Des Weiteren kann gezeigt werden, dass Analogie, ein Faktor der für Betonungsvariation in NN Komposita verantwortlich ist, auch bei der Betonung dreigliedrigen Komposita eine Rolle spielt. Ansätze, die die Betonung dreigliedriger Komposita zu erklären versuchen müssen daher die Existenz rechts betonter NNs berücksichtigen.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2012-03-27</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2011</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-6748</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät I Philosophische Fakultät</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="koesling.pdf" ddb:fileSize="1348005"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">957ca939a2bea8564a0970b212a36096</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/674/1/koesling.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/674</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>