<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>696</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Reactive scattering for H - + H 2 and H + + H 2 and its isotopologues : classical versus quantum investigation</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Dequan</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Wang</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Quantenchemie</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">quantum mechanic</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">energy surfaces</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">reaction probability</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">reaction cross section</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">540</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">In the present doctoral thesis, the reactive scattering for H- + H2 and H+ + H2 and its isotopologues&#13;
were investigated using different methods to solve the equations describing classical&#13;
and quantum mechanics. The studies aimed at providing insights into elementary reactions,&#13;
and may even go beyond these to more complex chemical reactions. The main results in this&#13;
dissertation can be summarized as follows:&#13;
In Chapter 2 the equations solving problems in quasi-classical mechanics were described,&#13;
which led to the definition of energy dependent reaction probabilities &#13;
and&#13;
reaction cross sections.&#13;
The formalism for time-dependent methods for the investigation of scattering processes was&#13;
presented in Chapter 3. In this section we discussed how to use the time-dependent quantum&#13;
wavepacket method to study the A-BC system. The dependence of the reaction probabilities&#13;
 on the total angular momenta J was calculated to obtain information about the&#13;
integral reactive cross section.&#13;
The potential energy surfaces (PESs) for H3+ and H3- were described in Chapter 4. For the&#13;
H3+ system, a cut through the potential energy surface (PES) in the asymptotic region was&#13;
presented. For the H3- system three available ab initio potential energy surfaces have been used&#13;
in the applications: a) Stärck and Meyer (SM-PES), b) Panda and Sathyamurthy (PS-PES),&#13;
and c) Ayouz et al. (AY-PES). The differences in the PESs were investigated.&#13;
In the beginning of Chapter 5 the H+ + H2(v=0-5, j=0) collision was investigated nonadiabatically.&#13;
By comparison of the reaction probabilities using adiabatic and non-adiabatic&#13;
representations of the potential energy surfaces, it was found that, at low collision energies,&#13;
the reaction preferentially occurs adiabatically, but at higher collision energies non-adiabatic&#13;
effects have to be taken into account.&#13;
Reaction probabilities and reaction cross sections for the collision H- with H2 and its isotopologues&#13;
using quasi-classical trajectories and quantum wavepackets were presented in the main&#13;
part of Chapter 5. It was found that, at low collision energies, the reaction probabilities&#13;
using SM-PES and AY-PES are very similar. The reaction probabilities based on the PS-PES&#13;
are lower than those based on the SM-PES and AY-PES. At lower collision energies the reaction&#13;
cross sections calculated with SM-PES are higher than those calculated with PS-PES.&#13;
The reaction cross sections investigated with quasi-classical trajectories are higher than those&#13;
calculated with quantum wavepackets (using the same potential).&#13;
The last section of Chapter 5 showed results for the collision of H- and D- with HD. The total&#13;
I&#13;
reaction probabilities, the reaction cross sections, and the product ratios were determined using&#13;
quasi-classical trajectories. One can learn from these calculations that for the H- + HD(v=0-1, j=0) reaction and low collision energies, the main product are H2 + D-. At high collision&#13;
energies, the product channel HD + H- is slightly dominant. For the collision of D- with HD&#13;
and low collision energies the product channel HD + D- is strongly favored, but in the high&#13;
collision energy range, the product channel D2 + H- dominates.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013-01-17</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-6960</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät IV Naturwissenschaftlich-Technische Fakultät</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="wang.pdf" ddb:fileSize="7593845"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">d14cc64d82bffa9afb647a4bb85535b4</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/696/1/wang.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/696</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>