<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>713</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Development of a confocal line scanning sensor</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Entwicklung eines konfokalen Zeilenscanners</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Sirichanok</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Chanbai</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Optische Messtechnik</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Konfokal</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Scheimpflug</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Zeilenscanner</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Rauheitsmessung</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Optische Messtechnik</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Confocal</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Scheimpflug</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">optical measuring system</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">line scanner</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">620</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">Surface characteristics are of vital importance for predicting the product life time and surface functionality, or even improving the manufacturing procedure. In consequence, this thesis focuses on the surface inspection using a non-contact technique.&#13;
&#13;
The principle of Confocal Microscopy(CM) enables light microscopes to gain depth information through what is known as depth discrimination ability. Among the other optical inspection techniques, the principle of confocal microscopy allows a parallel and motionless depth scanning scheme to be developed. The chromatic confocal point sensor is one prominent example of a parallel depth scanning scheme. However, this technique requires a separate analysis unit to analyze light of different wavelengths. The complication and relatively low efficiency of light per wavelength can pose a limit on developing a simplified configuration and a cost effective unit.&#13;
&#13;
Therefore, a novel approach to incorporate a tilted plane technique in a confocal imaging system is proposed in this thesis, namely a Confocal Line Scanning Sensor (CLSS). A parallel and motionless depth scanning scheme is then achieved with a cost-effective technique, resulting in a greatly simplified and robust configuration.&#13;
&#13;
This thesis is devoted to establish new knowledge on incorporating a tilted plane technique in a confocal imaging system. A novel approach to explain and to correct the variation of the magnification inherent in a tilted plane system, known as keystone distortion, is proposed. Moreover, particular data processing and calibrations are developed to support the new concept. Here, the Scheimpflug's principle is first applied with confocal microscopy, whereas selected well-known theories are also used to support the system design and construction.&#13;
&#13;
Finally, the experiments demonstrate that a tilted plane technique can successfully be incorporated in a confocal imaging system. In addition, the performance of the CLSS is evaluated through a series of experiments.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Die Oberflächeneigenschaften eines Produktes sind genauso entscheidend für die Vorhersage der Produktlebensdauer und der Oberflächenfunktionalität wie für die Optimierung des Herstellungsprozesses. Daher befasst sich diese Arbeit mit der berührungslosen Oberflächenmesstechnik.&#13;
&#13;
Das Prinzip der Konfokalmikroskopie (CM) ermöglicht es dank seiner tiefendis-kriminierenden Eigenschaften mit Lichtmikroskopen Tiefeninformation zu erhalten. Die Konfokalmikroskopie erlaubt die Entwicklung einer parallelen statischen Tiefenabtastung ohne bewegte Teile. Chromatische-konfokale Punktsensoren sind ein bekanntes Beispiel hierfür. Sie benötigen jedoch ein separates Spektrometer zur Analyse der verschiedenen Wellenlängenanteile. Dessen komplexer Aufbau und die realtiv geringe Lichtausbeute je Wellenlänge macht es schwierig einfache und preiswerte Produkte zu entwickeln.&#13;
&#13;
Daher wird in dieser Arbeit ein neuer Ansatz unter Verwendung der Scheimp-flug-Technik in einem konfokalen Abbildungssystem, einen sogenannten konfokalen Zeilenscanner (CLSS), vorgestellt. Eine parallele statische Tiefenabtastung wird hier mit einer kostengünstigeren Technologie und einem robusteren Aufbau erreicht.&#13;
&#13;
Ein neuer Ansatz zur Erklärung und Korrektur der Vergrößerungsvariation, auch als Keystone-Verzeichnung bekannt, wird vorgestellt. Desweiteren werden Verfahren zur Datenauswertung und Kalibrierung entwickelt. Das Scheimpflug-Prinzip wird erstmals auf die Konfokalmikroskopie angewandt.&#13;
 &#13;
Schließlich wird experimentell gezeigt, dass die Scheimpflugtechnik erfolgreich in einem Konfokalsystem eingesetzt werden kann. Die Eigenschaften des Verfahrens werden experimentell evaluiert.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2012-10-21</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2012</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-7131</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Institut für Automatisierungstechnik</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="chanbai.pdf" ddb:fileSize="10171912"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">6b07584ccb1f87c623f5686799b147de</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/713/1/chanbai.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/713</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>