<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>745</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">The only good 'Indian' is a screened 'Indian'! : First Nations culture and its representation in contemporary Canadian TV series</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Der einzig gute 'Indianer' ist ein gefilmter 'Indianer'! : die Kultur der First Nations und ihre Darstellung in zeitgenössischen kanadischen Fernsehserien</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Katrin</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Maslona</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Fernsehserie</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">First Nations</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">TV series</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Canada</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">indigenous</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">791</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">With its contemporary TV series on its Indigenous Inhabitants, called the First Nations, Canada possesses a unique mediascape, especially in the view of the fact that these shows make it their business to propagate a realistic representation of Aboriginal culture. The interaction between First Inhabitants and Western conquerers offers many opportunities to create profound storylines indeed. At the same time commercial mass media like television shows with their penchant for stereotyping – in the case of the American Aboriginals e.g. the 'Stoic Indian,' the 'Noble Savage' or the 'Naive Pocahontas' – do not seem to qualify for a differentiated historical revision of a colonized country with obvious winners and losers. At first glance the wide and very heterogeneous audience of a whole country needs to be entertained. Yet, it is the declared goal of these progressive TV shows to subtly convey a new more positive self- and public image of the Canadian Aboriginals. Hence, the television series constantly have to maintain the balance between presenting enthralling fiction appealing to the masses and sensitively handling the often painful reality of a people at the periphery of society. To illuminate this walk on a tightrope this study at first concentrates on the socio-cultural history of the First Nations shaped by tribal gender roles, a reciprocal relationship to nature, oral traditions and the final destruction of this cosmos. Based on this historical background as well as ideologies like Westo- and Mediacentrism and TV production techniques, this work then examines how the Canadian First Nations manage to employ seemingly hostile television mechanisms for their own benefit. Therefore, the subtexts of the drama series Moccasin Flats (2003-2006) and renegedepress.com (2004-2008) as well as the sitcoms The Rez (1996-1998), Hank Williams First Nation (2006) and Moose TV (2007) are analysed.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Kanada besitzt mit seinen zeitgenössischen Fernsehserien über seine Ureinwohner, die First Nations, eine einzigartige Medienlandschaft, nicht zuletzt deswegen, weil sich diese Formate zumeist um eine wirklichkeitsnahe Darstellung der indigenen Kultur bemühen. Grundsätzlich bietet das Aufeinandertreffen der First Nations und der westlichen Eroberer viele Möglichkeiten tiefgründige Storylines zu kreieren. Gleichzeitig erscheinen aber gerade kommerzielle Massenmedien wie TV Serien mit ihrem Hang zu Stereotypenbildung – im Falle der amerikanischen Ureinwohner zum Beispiel der 'Stoische Indianer,' der 'Noble Wilde' oder die 'Naive Pocahontas' – auf den ersten Blick als denkbar ungeeignet für die differenzierte Geschichtsaufarbeitung eines kolonisierten Landes mit scheinbar eindeutigen Gewinnern und Verlierern. Vordergründig muss zuallererst ein möglichst breites, heterogenes Publikum unterhalten werden. Doch das große Ziel dieser progressiven Serien ist es letztlich ein neues, positiveres Selbst- und Fremdbild der kanadischen Ureinwohner zu vermitteln. Folglich müssen diese TV Formate konstant zwischen massentauglicher Fiktion und authentischer Realitätsbewältigung balancieren. Um diesen Drahtseilakt zu beleuchten, befasst sich diese Arbeit zunächst mit der sozio-kulturellen Historie der First Nations, die von Stammeskultur bedingten Geschlechterrollen, einem reziproken Verhältnis zur Natur, oralen Traditionen und der Zerstörung dieses Kosmos durch die westliche Welt geprägt ist. Auf der Basis dieser geschichtlichen Hintergründe einerseits und Ideologien wie Westo- und Mediacentrism  sowie TV-Produktionstechnikern andererseits, wird untersucht, wie es den First Nations gelingt, das vermeintlich feindliche Medium Fernsehen für die eigenen Zwecke zu nutzen. Dazu werden die Subtexte der Dramen Moccasin Flats (2003-2006) und renegedepress.com (2004-2008) sowie der Sitcoms The Rez (1996-1998), Hank Williams First Nation (2006) und Moose TV (2007) untersucht.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2011-01-24</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2011</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-7458</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät I Philosophische Fakultät</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="maslona.pdf" ddb:fileSize="10997968"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">b226f5198cf60c8531ef2a0a8bf552c2</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/745/1/maslona.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/745</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>