<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>780</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Wie nutzen Kinder digitale Medien? : Fallstudien der alltäglichen Nutzung von Computer und Internet durch 9- bis 10-jährige Kinder</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" ddb:type="translated" lang="eng">How do children use digital media? : case studies of the everyday use of computer and internet by children aged 9-10</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Kai</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Schubert</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Kind</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">digitale Medien</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Medienpädagogik</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">child</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">digital media</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">media pedagogy</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">everyday</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">case studies</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">302</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Seit Kinder Computer nutzen wird darüber kontrovers diskutiert. In der&#13;
gesellschaftlichen Debatte wird oft über die Wirkung von Spielkonsolen,&#13;
Computern und des Internet gestritten. Dabei folgen wissenschaftliche&#13;
Untersuchungen zur Mediennutzung von Kindern häufig ausschließlich&#13;
quantitativen Paradigmen. Ein differenzierender Blick auf die Nutzungs-&#13;
und Aneignungspraxis digitaler Medien durch 9- bis 10-jährige Kinder in&#13;
Deutschland fehlt jedoch. Diese Lücke mit Hilfe qualitativ erhobener und&#13;
ausgewerteter Fallstudien zu schließen, ist Aufgabe der vorliegenden&#13;
Untersuchung. Folgende Punkte bilden in diesen ausführlichen Fallstudien&#13;
die Leitfragen: Wie, wo und wann nutzen 9- bis 10-jährige Kinder den&#13;
Computer und andere digitale Medien in ihrem Alltag? Welche Rolle spielen&#13;
die verschiedenen Medienwelten Familie, Peergroup und Schule sowie weitere&#13;
Bezugspersonen der Kinder bei der Aneignung digitaler Medien? Wie steht&#13;
die Nutzung digitaler Medien im Verhältnis zu den „klassischen“,&#13;
„analogen“ Medien? Wie eignen sich Kinder digitale Medien an? Wie&#13;
unterscheidet sich diese Aneignung im Vergleich zu anderen Medien? Die&#13;
Arbeit verfolgt einen interdisziplinären Forschungsansatz und widmet sich&#13;
bei den genannten Fragestellungen Themen, die sowohl für die Informatik&#13;
als auch für Pädagogik und Medienforschung von hoher Relevanz sind. Der&#13;
Schwerpunkt liegt dabei auf der Nutzung und Aneignung und nicht auf der&#13;
Wirkung von Medien.&#13;
 &#13;
Für die Untersuchung wird auf Methoden der qualitativen Sozialforschung&#13;
zurückgegriffen. Als Werkzeuge kommen verschiedene Interviewformen und die&#13;
teilnehmende Beobachtung zum Einsatz. Hervorzuheben ist hier das&#13;
sogenannte „interaktive Interview “, welches aufgrund der Anforderungen&#13;
des Forschungsfeldes im Rahmen dieser Arbeit entwickelt wurde. Als eine&#13;
Art Mischform bereits bestehender Methoden ermöglicht das interaktive&#13;
Interview einen besseren Zugang zum Feld und die Erhebung valider Daten.&#13;
Bei der Auswertung des empirischen Materials werden dem Ansatz der&#13;
Grounded Theory folgend mehrere Schlüsselkategorien, Dimensionen und&#13;
Eigenschaften herausgearbeitet, die eine systematische Beschreibung&#13;
einzelner Phänomene in den jeweiligen Fallstudien ermöglichen. In den&#13;
Fallstudien werden insgesamt zehn Kinder untersucht, von denen drei für&#13;
die Entwicklung der Schlüsselkategorien ausgewählt und kontrastierend&#13;
ausführlicher gegenübergestellt werden. Die Schlüsselkategorien bilden&#13;
dabei die Mediennutzung des Kindes, die Mediennutzung der Familie, die&#13;
Medienaneignung des Kindes und die Medienerziehung des Kindes.&#13;
 &#13;
Als Fazit ergibt sich ein deutlich differenziertes Bild der Bandbreite von&#13;
Nutzungs- und Aneignungspraktiken bei Kindern. Die Mediennutzung der&#13;
Kinder zeichnet sich durch eine große Vielfalt aus und ist einem&#13;
dauerhaften Wandel unterworfen. Bei der alltäglichen Nutzung ist die&#13;
jeweilige Medienwelt von entscheidender Bedeutung, in welcher sich das&#13;
Kind gerade befindet. In diesen Medienwelten gelten sehr unterschiedliche&#13;
Regeln, deren Bewusstwerden einen wichtigen Anteil an der Sozialisation&#13;
der Kinder hat. Besonders hervorzuheben ist hier die Vorbildwirkung der&#13;
elterlichen Nutzung der verschiedenen Medien. Neben den bestehenden drei&#13;
Medienwelten Familie, Peergroup und Schule kann das Internet als eine&#13;
neue, vierte Medienwelt definiert werden: sie hat Einfluss auf alle&#13;
anderen Medienwelten und existiert in den meisten Fällen nicht losgelöst&#13;
von diesen. Dabei stellen sich die bestehenden Medienwelten der&#13;
zunehmenden alltäglichen Bedeutung des Internets und den damit verbundenen&#13;
Herausforderungen sehr unterschiedlich. Übergreifend lässt sich dagegen in&#13;
allen Medienwelten ein neuer Typ von Habitus bei der Nutzung digitaler&#13;
Medien beobachten. Dieser „digitale Habitus“ ist dabei nicht als getrennt&#13;
vom sonstigen Habitus des Kindes zu betrachten, vielmehr wird er neuer&#13;
Bestandteil desselben: Die anfangs spielerische Nutzung und Geheimhaltung&#13;
von Passwörtern zum Schutz der eigenen Privatsphäre sind ein typisches&#13;
Merkmal des digitalen Habitus. Weitere Merkmale wie beispielsweise&#13;
Strategien zum Korrigieren von Fehlern (durch Neustart bzw. „Neumachen“)&#13;
können dabei auch als originär betrachtet werden und bilden einen&#13;
wichtigen Anknüpfungspunkt für weitere Untersuchungen. Zu den wichtigsten&#13;
Schlussfolgerungen gehört für die Informatik, digitale Medien für und mit&#13;
Kindern zu gestalten, die eine gemeinsame Nutzungskultur von Kindern und&#13;
Eltern fördern. In der Pädagogik besteht eine Herausforderung darin, sich&#13;
zukünftig in der Lehrerausbildung wie auch den Schulen selbst verstärkt&#13;
mit Spielen und sozialen Medien auseinanderzusetzen. Forschungsmethodisch&#13;
spielen bei der Untersuchung sozialer Medien zunehmend auch ethische&#13;
Probleme eine Rolle: Die Vermischung von Massen- und&#13;
Individualkommunikation in den sozialen Medien konfrontiert Forscher bei&#13;
der Erhebung, Auswertung und Veröffentlichung von empirischen Daten mit&#13;
neuen und noch ungelösten Fragen.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">Children using computers has been a controversial subject from the outset.&#13;
Although public debate often argues about the effect of game consoles,&#13;
computers and the Internet, scientific studies concerning children’s media&#13;
use are almost always based on exclusively quantitative paradigms. On the&#13;
other hand, differentiated analysis of the use and appropriation of&#13;
digital media by 9- and 10-year-old children in Germany is very scarce.&#13;
The present study intends to close this gap using qualitative case studies&#13;
which have been collected and evaluated. The key questions in these&#13;
detailed case studies are composed of the following points: How, where and&#13;
when do 9- and 10-year old children use the computer and other digital&#13;
media in their everyday lives? Which role do the various media worlds&#13;
(i.e. family, peer group, school and various other important people in the&#13;
children’s lives) play in the appropriation of digital media? How do&#13;
children use digital media compared to “classic”, “analogue” media? How do&#13;
children appropriate digital media? What is the difference between this&#13;
appropriation in comparison with the appropriation of other media? This&#13;
study follows an interdisciplinary research approach which, while&#13;
clarifying the afore mentioned key points, focuses on topics which are&#13;
highly relevant for computer science as well as for pedagogy and media&#13;
research. The main focus hereby is on the use and appropriation of media,&#13;
not on their effects.&#13;
&#13;
The study makes use of qualitative methods of social research, using tools&#13;
which include various types of interview and participatory observation.&#13;
One particularly important method is the so-called “interactive interview”&#13;
which was developed in the course of this study to answer the requirements&#13;
of the research field. As a kind of hybrid composed of already existing&#13;
methods, the interactive interview allows both better access to the field&#13;
as well as the elicitation of valid data. For the evaluation of the&#13;
empirical material, several key categories, dimensions and properties are&#13;
elicited according to the grounded theory method, which allow for a&#13;
systematic description of the individual phenomena within the respective&#13;
case studies. A total of ten children formed the core of the case studies&#13;
and, of these, three were chosen for the development of the key&#13;
categories. The cases were subsequently contrasted with each other in&#13;
greater detail. The key categories were Children’s Media Use, Families’&#13;
Media Use, Children’s Media Appropriation and Children’s Media&#13;
Education.&#13;
&#13;
The result is a clearly differentiated picture of the spectrum of&#13;
children’s media use and appropriation practices. Children’s media use is&#13;
characterized by great diversity and is subject to constant change. In&#13;
everyday use, it is the respective media world by which the child is&#13;
currently surrounded which is of vital importance. Each media world&#13;
applies its own, different rules and the awareness of this plays an&#13;
important part in children’s socialization. Particular focus hereby is on&#13;
the role model effect of parental use of the diverse media. In addition to&#13;
the three existing media worlds of family, peer group and school, the&#13;
internet can be defined as a new, fourth media world: it influences all&#13;
the other media worlds and in most cases does not exist autonomously. At&#13;
the same time, the existing media worlds face up to the increasing&#13;
importance of the internet in everyday life and the challenges involved in&#13;
very different ways. In general, a new type of habitus can be observed&#13;
concerning the use of digital media in all media worlds. This “digital&#13;
habitus” is not to be discerned as distinct from the children’s other&#13;
habitus. On the contrary it is, in fact, rather to be seen as a new aspect&#13;
of these habitus: the initially playful use and secrecy concerning&#13;
passwords that protect personal privacy are typical features of digital&#13;
habitus. Additional attributes, e.g. strategies for the correction of&#13;
mistakes (by rebooting, or “starting again”) can be seen here as original&#13;
and provide an important link to a starting point for further studies. One&#13;
of the most important conclusions for computer science is that digital&#13;
media should be designed for and with children. This calls for a common&#13;
culture of use by children and their parents alike. One future challenge&#13;
for pedagogy will be for teachers in the course of their training as well&#13;
as for schools themselves to focus intensively on games and social media.&#13;
Seen from a research methodological point of view, it would appear to be&#13;
ethical issues which play a role when studying social media: researchers&#13;
eliciting, evaluating and publishing empirical data are being confronted&#13;
with new and as yet unsolved issues due to the blending of mass- and&#13;
individual communication in social media.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013-09-04</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-7801</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">ger</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät III - Wirtschaftswissenschaften, Wirtschaftsinformatik und Wirtschaftsrecht</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="schubert_kai.pdf" ddb:fileSize="5536571"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">4a52054fe48544274b84e02ac7f66007</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/780/1/schubert_kai.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/780</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>