<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>800</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Depth resolved investigation of ion beam induced pattern formation on silicon using X-ray methods</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Tiefenaufgelöste Untersuchung der Ionenstrahl induzierten Musterbildung auf Silizium unter Verwendung von Röntgenverfahren</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Behnam</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Khanbabaee Patekhour</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Ionenstrahl</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Ionenstrahl induzierte Musterbildung</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Ion implantation</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">surface patterning</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Silicon</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">X-ray</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">530</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">In the present work, ion beam induced pattern formation on silicon surfaces is investigated, which was induced by off-normal irradiation of Fe ions. It is observed that the self-organized surface patterning takes place when the ion fluence exceeds a certain limit. The influence of the ion parameters on the patterning mechanism was investigated via monitoring of the near surface area where incorporated Fe ions play a dominant role. In a first step, ion beam induced surface density variation was studied as a function of ion parameters. Conventional X-ray reflectivity revealed the formation of a nm sub-surface layer with incorporated Fe atoms. Using X-ray reflectivity, no major dependence of the surface density on the ion fluence could be obtained. Thus, a new powerful technique with higher surface sensitivity was applied based on extremely asymmetrical X-ray diffraction methods. The density information was extracted from the shift of the diffraction peak caused by refraction of the X-ray beam at the air-sample interface. Simulations based on the dynamical theory of X-ray diffraction revealed a decrease of the density for increasing ion fluence in a region close to the surface. It shows that there is a threshold value for ion fluence leading to reduction of surface density. The obtained results reveal that the change of local density contributes to the development of the pattern on the surface. In a second step, Fe-silicide formation in various stoichiometries was investigated in the amorphized surface region of crystalline Si(100) after irradiation with Fe ions. A depth resolved analysis of chemical states of Si and Fe atoms in the near surface region was performed by combining X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy and X-ray absorption spectroscopy using synchrotron radiation. The formation of silicide bonds of different stoichiometric composition changing from an Fe-rich silicide (Fe3Si) close to the surface into a Si-rich silicide (FeSi2) towards to the inner interfaces was observed. This observation shows that the presence of chemically bonded iron close to the surface is an important prerequisite of pattern formation. In a third step, the recrystallization of the pre-formed Fe-silicides of various stoichiometries was investigated below the amorphized surface of crystalline Si(100). A thermal annealing process was applied in the range between room temperature and 800°C. Depth profiling by grazing incidence X-ray diffraction confirmed that a ε-FeSi phase was formed close to the surface changing to a β-FeSi2 phase with lower Fe content at larger depths. Both phases are distributed with different ratios within the Fe-Si layer at smooth and patterned surfaces, corresponding to low and high ion fluences, respectively. In the last step, the obtained results were examined for pattern formation on Si(001) surfaces under normal incident Kr ion bombardment with simultaneous incorporation of Fe atoms. It was verified that the surface patterning takes place only when the incorporated Fe concentration again exceeds a certain limit. For a high Fe concentration the ripple formation is accompanied by the enrichment of Fe atoms at the top part of ripples, whereas no such Fe enhancement is found for a low Fe concentration at samples with smooth surfaces. Modeling of the measured X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy and X-ray absorption spectroscopy spectra reveals the appearance of different silicide phases with a decreasing Fe content from top towards the volume.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">In der vorliegenden Arbeit wird die Musterbildung auf Siliziumoberflächen durch den Beschuss mit Eisenionen unter schrägem Einfallswinkeln untersucht. Experimentell wird beobachtet, dass es zu selbstorganisierter Strukturbildung an der Oberfläche kommt, wenn die Ionendosis (Fluenz) einen bestimmten Schwellenwert überschreitet. In dieser Arbeit wird der Einfluss der Ionenstrahl-Parameter auf die Musterbildung untersucht. Insbesondere wird die Region nahe der Oberfläche, in welcher die Fe-Ionen eine entscheidende Rolle bei der Musterbildung spielen, mittels Oberflächensensitiver Rontgenstreuung untersucht. In einem ersten Schritt wird das Dichteprofil nahe der Oberfläche als Funktion von Ionenenergie und Fluenz untersucht. Rontgenreflektometrie zeigt dabei die Ausbildung eine mit Eisen angereicherten Schicht in den ersten Nanometern unterhalb der Oberfläche, jedoch wird keine ausgeprägte Abhängigkeit von der Ionenfluenz festgestellt. Um die Oberflächensensitivität weiter zu erhohen, wird eine neue Methode basierend auf der extrem asymmetrischen Rontgenbeugung eingesetzt. Diese erlaubt die Ermittelung kleinster Dichtevariationen infolge des Nachweises kleinster Winkelverschiebungen des gebeugten Rontgenstrahls auf Grund der Brechung des Rontgenstrahls an der Oberfläche. Durch Simulationen mit Hilfe der dynamischen Theorie der Rontgenbeugung wird eine mit steigender Fluenz zunehmende Verringerung der Dichte nahe der Oberfläche nachgewiesen. Daraus wird gefolgert, dass die Massendichte an der Oberfläche unter Einfluss der Musterbildung abnimmt. In einem zweiten Schritt wird die Ausbildung von Eisen-Siliziden verschiedener Stochiometrie in der amorphisierten Region nahe der Oberfläche untersucht. Die Kombination von Rontgen-Photoemissions-Spektroskopie und Rontgenabsorptionsspektroskopie mittels Synchrotronstrahlung erlaubt eine tiefenaufgeloste Bestimmung der chemischen Bindungszustände von Si und Fe atomen nahe der Oberfläche. Es wird gezeigt, dass sich nahe der Oberfläche Eisenreiches Silizid (Fe3Si), in großerer Tiefe nahe der Grenzsschicht zu noch kristallinem Silizium jedoch vermehrt Siliziumreiches FeSi2 Silizid bilded. Dieser Nachweis belegt, dass chemisch gebundenes Eisen eine Vorbedingung zur Musterbildung darstellt. Die gebildeten Phasen mit unterschiedlichem Fe-Si Verhältnis auf glatten und strukturierten Oberflächen entsprechen niedrigen und hohen Ionen Flüssen. In einem dritten Schritt wird die Rekristallisation dieser Eisensilizide während thermischem Ausheizens bei Temperaturen bis 800°C untersucht. Tiefenaufgeloste Messungen mittels Rontgenbeugung unter streifendem Einfall (GID) belegen, dass sich nahe der Oberfläche ε-FeSi bildet, in großerer Tiefe jedoch β-FeSi2 mit geringerem Fe-Gehalt. Verschiedene gebildeten Phasen mit unterschiedlichen Verhältnis im Fe-Si Schicht auf glatten und strukturierten Oberflächen entsprach niedrige und hohe Ionen Flüssen. Zuletzt wird die Musterbildung auf Si(001) Oberflächen nach Krypton-Sputtering bei gleichzeitigem Eisen-Eintrag untersucht. Es zeigt sich, dass es auch in diesem Fall nur zu Musterbildung kommt, wenn die Konzentration von Eisenatomen an der Oberfläche einen Schwellenwert überschreitet. Für hohe Eisenkonzentrationen kommt es zur Ausbildung periodischer Ripple-Muster mit einer Anreicherung von Eisen nahe der "Gipfel" der Ripples. Photoelektronen-Spektroskopie und Rontgenabsorptionsspektroskopie zeigen auch hier die Ausbildung von Silizidphasen mit abnehmendem Eisengehalt von der Oberfläche in Richtung auf das Volumen.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2014-04-29</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2014</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-8001</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät IV - Naturwissenschaftlich-Technische Fakultät</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="khanbabaee.pdf" ddb:fileSize="8904933"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">a9fe33475ec1b973ef164dacf7fdc3a0</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/800/1/khanbabaee.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/800</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>