<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>839</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Temporal quantum correlations and hidden variable models</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Costantino</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Budroni</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Quantenmechanik</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Quantum Mechanics</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Quantum Correlations</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Contextuality</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Nonlocality</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Sequential Measurements</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">530</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">This thesis is devoted to the investigation of the differences between the predictions of classical and quantum theory. More precisely, we shall analyze such differences starting from their consequences on quantities with a clear empirical meaning, such as probabilities, or relative frequencies, that can be directly observed in experiments.&#13;
  Different kind of classical probability theories, or hidden variable theories, corresponding to different physical constraints imposed on the measurement scenario are discussed, namely, locality,noncontextuality and macroscopic realism. Each of these theories predicts bounds on the strength of correlations among different variables, and quantum mechanical predictions violate such bounds, thus revealing a stark contrast with our classical intuition.&#13;
 Our work starts with the investigation of the set of classical probabilities by means of the correlation polytope approach, which provides a minimal and optimal set of bounds for classical correlations. In order to overcome some of the computational difficulties associated with it, we develop an alternative method that avoid the direct computation of the polytope and we apply it to Bell and noncontextuality scenarios showing its advantages both for analytical and numerical computations.&#13;
 A different notion of optimality is then discussed for noncontextuality scenarios that provide a state-independent violation: Optimal expression are those maximizing the ratio between the quantum and the classical value. We show that this problem can be formulated as a linear program and solved with standard numerical techniques. Moreover, optimal inequalities for the cases analyzed are also proven to be part of the minimal set described above.&#13;
 Subsequently, we provide a general method to analyze quantum correlations in the sequential measurement scenario, which allows us to compute the maximal correlations. Such a method has a direct application for computation of maximal quantum violations of Leggett-Garg inequalities, i.e., the bounds for correlation in a macroscopic realist theories, and it is relevant in the analysis of noncontextuality tests, where sequential measurements are usually employed.&#13;
 Finally, we discuss a possible application of the above results for the construction of dimension witnesses, i.e., as a certification of the minimal dimension of the Hilbert spaces needed to explain the arising of certain quantum correlations.to Bell and noncontextuality scenarios showing its advantages both for analytical and numerical computations.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Diese Doktorarbeit befasst sich mit der Untersuchung der unterschiedlichen Vorhersagen von klassischen Theorien und Quantenmechanik. &#13;
Es werden verschiedene klassische Wahrscheinlichkeitstheorien oder Theorien, die auf der Existenz versteckter Variablen basieren, diskutiert und besonders auf ihre Vorhersagen bezüglich der möglichen Stärke der Korrelationen zwischen verschiedenen Variablen eingegangen. Die klassischen Theorien machen dabei unterschiedliche physikalischen Annahmen wie Lokalität, Nichtkontextualität oder makroskopischer Realismus. Für jede dieser Theorien sagt die Quantenmeachnik stärkere Korrelationen voraus, die die klassischen Schranken verletzen und damit im Widerspruch zu unserer klassisch geprägten Intuition stehen.&#13;
 Unsere Arbeit beginnt mit der Untersuchung der Menge von klassischen Wahrscheinlichkeiten mittels des Korrelations-Polytop-Verfahrens, welches einen minimalen und optimalen Satz an Grenzen für klassische Korrelationen liefert. Um einige der mit diesem Verfahren verbundenen rechnerischen Schwierigkeiten zu überwinden, entwickeln wir eine alternative Methode, die die direkte Berechnung des Polytops umgeht. Angewendet auf Bell- und Kontextualitätsszenarien zeigen wir die Vorteile unserer Methode, sowohl bezüglich analytischer, als auch numerischer Berechnungen. Danach wird eine andere Möglichkeit betrachtet, Optimalität für Nichtkontextualitätsungleichungen zu definieren, die eine zustandsunabhängige Verletzung aufweisen: Optimale Ungleichungen sind solche, die das Verhältnis zwischen quantenmachanischem und klassischem Wert maximieren. Wir zeigen, dass dieses Problem als lineares Programm formuliert und mit standardmäßigen, numerischen Methoden gelöst werden kann. Darüber  hinaus beweisen wir, dass die optimalen Ungleichungen für  die betrachteten Fälle jene sind, die Teil des oben beschriebenen minimalen Satzes von Grenzflächen sind.&#13;
 Anschließend stellen wir eine allgemeine Methode vor mit der man Quantenkorrelationen bei sequentiellen Messungen analysieren kann und die maximalen Korrelationen berechnen kann. Ein solches Verfahren hat als direkte Anwendung die Berechnung maximaler Quantenverletzung von Leggett-Garg Ungleichungen, d.h. der Grenzen für Korrelationen in Theorien, die auf der Annahme des makroskopischem Realismus basieren. Zudem ist diese Methode relevant in der analytischen Betrachtung von Kontextualitätstests, in denen üblicherweise sequentielle Messungen verwendet werden.&#13;
 Abschließend diskutieren wir für die obigen Resultate Anwendungen bei der Konstruktion von Zeugenoperatoren für die Dimension von Quantensystemen. Damit ist es möglich, die minimale Dimension des Hilbertraums zu zertifizieren, die nötig ist, um das Auftreten von gegebenen Quantenkorrelationen zu erklären.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2014-09-19</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2014</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-8395</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät IV - Naturwissenschaftlich-Technische Fakultät</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Dissertation_Costantino_Budroni.pdf" ddb:fileSize="2173188"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">aa3ab8a0549f64c72c12a7a06307c6ae</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/839/1/Dissertation_Costantino_Budroni.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/839</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>