<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>913</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">Structure and electrical response of GaAs nanowires : looking for a correlation at the nano-scale</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Genziana</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Bussone-Grifone</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Nanodraht</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Röntgennanodiffraktion</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">nanowire</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">gallium arsenide</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">x-ray diffraction</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">optoelectronics</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">530</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">For applications of nanowires in optoelectronic devices their controlled positioning onto substrates during growth is often required, as well as the control of their polytype mixture and strain state. Therefore a deep comprehension of the growth and preparation mechanisms is essential. Multiple investigation techniques at the nano-scale have been developed nowadays with the goal to correlate the structure and the physical response of nanostructures. The first aim of this work is the structural investigation of individual nanowires grown on GaAs substrates by molecular beam epitaxy. The specific positioning of the nanowires during growth has been achieved by Au-implantation into the substrate. X-ray nano-diffraction in grazing incidence diffraction geometry was used to investigate the in-plane strain at different positions, along the growth axis of individual nanowires. It was found that the nanowires are twisted about their growth axis with respect to the substrate. As expected, the crystal lattice of the nanowires is totally relaxed. Under surface diffraction conditions, the upper most layers of the growth substrate could be investigated at the same time. Here, regions at different distances from the Au-implanted area revealed the presence of a compressive strain, decreasing further away from the nanowire base. In prior studies of semiconductor nanowires it has been shown that the value of specific physical parameters strongly differ frombulk materials. For example, the high aspect ratio and the mixture of polytypes can significantly influence electrical and optical properties of GaAs nanowires. Moreover, nanowires standing in upright position onto their growth substrate revealed their importance in modern devices. The second aim of this thesis is to correlate the electrical and structural parameters of individual as-grown nanowires onto their growth substrate. This was achieved by measuring the electrical characteristics of single nanowires in a focused ion beam chamber; and by determining their polytype composition using coplanar X-ray nano-diffraction. The nanowires measured showed differing electrical characteristics. These differences have been successfully correlated with the number of zinc-blende and twinned zinc-blende units detected within single nanowires. The combination of the described techniques represents the main challenge of this work. Besides the difficulties of identifying individual nanowires in different experimental configurations; all electrical characteristics, linked to the contacting procedure of the nanowire, had to be understood and controlled. Electronic and optoelectronic applications often require specific sample preparations. Those may include the embedding of the nanostructures in a polymer matrix and the application of a top contact. As a third aim, symmetric and asymmetric X-ray diffraction revealed indirectly the presence of a preparation-induced average initial strain in the Benzocyclobutene polymer, by measuring an ensemble of embedded GaAs nanowires. This resulted in uniaxial strained embedded nanostructures, and was found to originate from the thermal processing of the polymer. The detected compression was shown to decrease under X-ray illumination and application of an external static electric field, which lead to the formation and reorientation of polar sub-molecules in the polymer.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Um Nanodrähte gezielt für optoelektronische Schaltungen anzuwenden, muss bereits beim Wachstum auf deren genaue Positionierung auf dem Substrat, auf die Polytype Verteilung im Nanodraht und auf dessen Verzerrungszustand geachtet werden. Deshalb ist ein tieferes Verständis der Wachstums und Präparationsmechanismen erforderlich. Der Einsatz einer Reihe von Untersuchungstechniken auf der Nanosskala wurden entwickelt, um physikalische Eigenschaften der Nanoobjekte mit deren Struktur zu korrelieren. Das erste Ziel der vorliegenden Arbeit liegt daher in der strukturellen Untersuchung einzelner, mittels Molekular Strahl Epitaxie auf GaAs Substraten gewachsener, Nanodrähte. In diesem Fall wurde die Positionierung der Drähte über eine räumlich selektive Implantation von Gold Atomen im Substrat erreicht. Röntgenbeugung unter streifendem Einfall mittels eines Nanostrahls wurde eingesetzt, um den Verzerrungszustand in der Substratebene an verschiedenen Positionen auf dem Substrat und entlang des Drahtes zu bestimmen. Dabei wurde festgestellt, dass die Nanodrähte entlang der Wachstumsrichtung leicht verdreht gegenüber dem Substrat wachsen. Wie erwartet ist dabei das Kristallgitter der Nanodrähte verzerrungsfrei. Infolge der extremen Oberflächensensitivität konnten gleichzeitig die obersten Gitterebenen des Substrats untersucht werden. Hierbei zeigte sich eine mit größer werdendem Abstand zum Au implantierten Gebiet kleiner werdende kompressible Deformation. Aus früheren Untersuchungen an Halbleiter Nanodrähten ist bekannt, dass die Größe vieler physikalischer Eigenschaften von der des Volumenmaterials abweicht. Zum Beispiel beeinflußt das große Seitenverhältnis und die strukturelleMischung verschiedener Polytypen signifikant die elektrischen und optischen Eigenschaften von GaAs Nanodrähten.Weiterhin spielt die Tatsache, dass die Drähte in aufrechter Position auf dem Substrate verbleiben können, eine große Rolle für deren Anwendung in modernen Bauelementen. Das zweite Ziel dieser Arbeit besteht in der Korrelation von elektrischen und strukturellen Eigenschaften einzelner Nanodrähte in ihrer Position auf dem Substrat. Diese Korrelation wurde erreicht, indem die elektrische Charakteristik ausgewählter Nanodrähte in einer Fokussierten Ionenstrahl Kammer gemessen und die Polytypzusammensetzung der gleichen Drähte mittels Röntgennanodiffraktion bestimmt wurde. Die gemessenen Nanodrähte zeigen eine unterschiedliche elektrische Charakteristik. Diese Unterschiede konnten erfolgreich mit der unterschiedlichen Zahl von Zinkblende und verzwillingter Zinkblende Struktureinheiten innerhalb der Nanodrähte korreliert werden. Die Kombination dieser beiden Techniken stellte die größte Herausforderung dieser Arbeit dar. Neben der Schwierigkeit der Identifizierung individueller Nanodrähte in unterschiedlichen experimentellen Konfigurationen, mußten die Einflußparameter der elektrischen Charakteristik, einschießlich der Kontaktierungsprobleme, verstanden und kontrolliert werden. Elektronische und optoelektronische Anwednungen fordern sehr oft eine spezielle Probenpräparation. Das schließt die Einbettung von Nanostrukturen in eine Polymermatrix und die Kontaktierung derselben mit ein. Als drittes Ziel dieser Arbeit wurde mit Hilfe der symmetrischen und asymmetrischen Röntgenbeugung nachgewiesen, dass Benzocyclobutene im Resultat des Einbettungsprozesses gegenüber demeingebetteten GaAs Nanodrähten elastisch verzerrt ist. Das Auftreten dieser einachsig deformierten eingebetten Nanostruktur wurde auf den thermischen Prozessschritt bei der Einbettung zurückgeführt. Es zeigte sich, dass die festgestellte Kompression unter Bestrahlung mit Röntgenlicht und bei gleichzeitig angelegtem elektrischen Feld zurückging. Dieser Effekt konnte mit der Formierung und Reoriertierung von polaren Sub-Molekülen im Polymer erklärt werden.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2015-02-06</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2014</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-9136</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät IV - Naturwissenschaftlich-Technische Fakultät</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Dissertation_Genziana_Bussone_Grifone.pdf" ddb:fileSize="55979350"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">125484aaa6e50f4530a65f9b5a611150</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/913/1/Dissertation_Genziana_Bussone_Grifone.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/913</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>