<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>934</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="eng">A new window to the universe? : searching for ultra-high-energy photons at the Pierre Auger Observatory</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Ein neues Fenster zum Universum? : die Suche nach ultrahochenergetischen Photonen am Pierre-Auger-Observatorium</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Marcus</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Niechciol</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">UHECR</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Astroteilchenphysik</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Astroparticle Physics</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:noScheme">Multivariate Analysis</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">530</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">The subject of the present thesis is the search for photons in the EeV range in cosmic-ray data collected at the Pierre Auger Observatory. Photons, in general, are the main messenger particles for the exploration of the Universe. An observation of photons in the EeV range, the existence of which is predicted by many current theories about the origin of Ultra-High-Energy Cosmic Rays (UHECRs), would not only open a new observational window to the Universe, but would also further our understanding of UHECRs in general. The Pierre Auger Observatory offers an unprecedented exposure to UHE particles and thus provides a unique opportunity to search for UHE photons. In order to distinguish extensive air showers induced by photons from the hadronic background, a combination of the observable Xmax, which is directly measured by the Fluorescence Detector (FD), and the novel observable Fgamma, which is determined from the signals recorded by the Surface Detector (SD), is employed. Both observables are combined in a multivariate Fisher discriminant analysis. Applying this analysis to data collected at the Pierre Auger Observatory between 2004 and 2012, one event with photon-like characteristics is found. From this result, upper limits on the fraction of photons in the total flux of cosmic rays in the EeV range are determined, which are on par with the most stringent limits set by previous analyses.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Gegenstand der vorliegenden Arbeit ist die Suche nach Photonen im EeV-Bereich in Daten des Pierre-Auger-Observatoriums. Photonen sind die wichtigsten Botschafterteilchen bei der Erforschung des Universums. Die Beobachtung von Photonen im EeV-Bereich, deren Existenz von vielen Theorien zur Herkunft von ultrahochenergetischer kosmischer Strahlung vorhergesagt wird, würde nicht nur ein neues Beobachtungsfenster zum Universum öffnen, sondern auch unser generelles Verständnis von kosmischer Strahlung vertiefen. Das Pierre-Auger-Observatorium bietet hervorragende Bedingungen für die Suche nach ultrahochenergetischen Photonen. Um Luftschauer, die von Photonen induziert wurden, vom hadronischen Untergrund zu trennen, wird eine Kombination der Observablen Xmax, die direkt mit den Fluoreszenzdetektoren gemessen werden kann, sowie der neuartigen Observable Fgamma verwendet. Die Observable Fgamma basiert auf den Signalen, die in den einzelnen Detektorstationen des Oberflächendetektors gemessen werden. Um beide Observablen zu kombinieren wird eine multivariate Fisher-Diskriminanzanalyse verwendet. Die Anwendung der Methode auf Daten, die zwischen 2004 und 2012 am Pierre-Auger-Observatorium aufgenommen wurden, ergibt ein Luftschauer-Ereignis mit photonartigen Eigenschaften. Es werden Obergrenzen auf den Anteil von Photonen im Gesamtfluss der kosmischen Strahlung im EeV-Bereich bestimmt, die vergleichbar sind mit den strengsten Obergrenzen aus früheren Analysen.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:dateAccepted xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2015-07-07</dcterms:dateAccepted>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2015</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">doctoralThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-9346</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">eng</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>thesis.doctoral</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät IV - Naturwissenschaftlich-Technische Fakultät</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Dissertation_Marcus_Niechciol.pdf" ddb:fileSize="47166164"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">bc355a148ab10fe34ebd4d69c6c427fb</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/934/1/Dissertation_Marcus_Niechciol.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/934</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>