<xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss xmlns:xMetaDiss="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/" xmlns:cc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:pc="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/pc/" xmlns:urn="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/urn/" xmlns:hdl="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/hdl/" xmlns:doi="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/doi/" xmlns:thesis="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:ddb="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/ddb/" xmlns:dini="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/type/" xmlns="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/subject/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:doc="http://www.lyncode.com/xoai" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.d-nb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/  http://files.dnb.de/standards/xmetadissplus/xmetadissplus.xsd"><id>952</id>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" lang="ger">Soziale Arbeit als "Menschenrechtsprofession"</dc:title>
   <dc:title xsi:type="ddb:titleISO639-2" ddb:type="translated" lang="eng">Social work as a "human rights profession"</dc:title>
   <dc:creator xsi:type="pc:MetaPers">
      <pc:person>
         <pc:name type="nameUsedByThePerson">
            <pc:foreName>Lisa Marie</pc:foreName>
            <pc:surName>Jacobi</pc:surName>
         </pc:name>
      </pc:person>
   </dc:creator>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:SWD">Sozialarbeit</dc:subject>
   <dc:subject xsi:type="xMetaDiss:DDC-SG">300</dc:subject>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="ger">Was haben Soziale Arbeit und Menschenrechte eigentlich miteinander zu tun? Wie ist der, in der Sozialen Arbeit vor allem in jüngerer und jüngster Zeit aufgekommene, Diskurs über ein Selbstverständnis als Menschenrechtsprofession zu verstehen? Zur Klärung dieser und ähnlicher Fragen versucht diese Arbeit einen kleinen Beitrag zu leisten. Hierzu werden im ersten Teil zunächst Menschenrechte einerseits sowie die Profession Soziale Arbeit andererseits losgelöst voneinander erörtert (jeweils unter Berücksichtigung der Dimensionen Begriffsverständnis, Geschichte sowie aktuelle Ausgestaltung). Anschließend werden mithilfe dieses ersten Teils Schnittmengen zwischen Menschenrechten und Sozialer Arbeit analysiert, welche dann wiederum als Überleitung zum zweiten Teil der Arbeit dienen. In diesem wird zu Beginn der aktuell stattfindende Diskurs über ein Selbstverständnis der Sozialen Arbeit als Menschenrechtsprofession systematisch aufgearbeitet, anschließend der Aspekt der Menschenrechtsbildung kurz erläutert, sowie abschließend Menschenrechte in ihrer Bedeutung für die sozialarbeiterische Praxis erörtert. Abschließend lässt sich so die Frage klären, ob die Soziale Arbeit denn tatsächlich inhärent als eine solche Menschenrechtsprofession zu verstehen ist bzw. welche Implikationen ein solches Verständnis für Wissenschaft und Praxis der Profession hätte.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dcterms:abstract xsi:type="ddb:contentISO639-2" lang="eng">What is the supposed, and especially recently within the profession much discussed, connection between human rights and the social work profession? How should one interpret the profession’s discourse about whether or not it wants to understand itself as a human rights profession? The work at hand attempts to make a small contribution towards answering these and similar questions.&#13;
In order to do this, the first part of this work starts out discussing human rights on the one hand and social work on the other hand separately from each other (each discussion taking into account the implications of terminology, history and current issues). Using the theoretical background knowledge gained from this first part, (historical) connections and similarities between human rights and social work are then analyzed in order to introduce the second part of this work, in which at first the previously mentioned existing social work profession’s discourse about inherently being a human rights profession is systematically presented. Thereafter, possible implications of a self-definition as a human rights profession are discussed, primarily in regards to the issues of human rights education as well as social work practice.&#13;
With this, the initial question of if and how social work can be understood as a human rights profession ultimately becomes answerable. Again, the implications of human rights based social work are discussed for both the theoretical and the applied sides of the profession.</dcterms:abstract>
   <dc:publisher xsi:type="cc:Publisher" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
      <cc:universityOrInstitution cc:GKD-Nr="509551-7">
         <cc:name>Universitätsbibliothek der Universität Siegen</cc:name>
         <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
      </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      <cc:address cc:Scheme="DIN5008">Adolf-Reichweinstr. 2, 57068 Siegen</cc:address>
   </dc:publisher>
   <dcterms:issued xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2015</dcterms:issued>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dini:PublType">bachelorThesis</dc:type>
   <dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Text</dc:type>
   <dini:version_driver>publishedVersion</dini:version_driver>
   <dc:identifier xsi:type="urn:nbn">urn:nbn:de:hbz:467-9529</dc:identifier>
   <dc:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-2">ger</dc:language>
   <dc:rights xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/static/license.txt</dc:rights>
   <thesis:degree>
      <thesis:level>bachelor</thesis:level>
      <thesis:grantor xsi:type="cc:Corporate" type="dcterms:ISO3166" countryCode="DE">
         <cc:universityOrInstitution>
            <cc:name>Universität Siegen</cc:name>
            <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            <cc:department>
               <cc:name>Fakultät II (Bildung, Architektur, Künste)</cc:name>
               <cc:place>Siegen</cc:place>
            </cc:department>
         </cc:universityOrInstitution>
      </thesis:grantor>
   </thesis:degree>
   <ddb:contact ddb:contactID="L6000-0732"/>
   <ddb:fileNumber>1</ddb:fileNumber>
   <ddb:fileProperties ddb:fileName="Lisa_Marie_Jacobi.pdf" ddb:fileSize="636556"/>
   <ddb:checksum ddb:type="MD5">c91055e4eb965e2d72025c62e0903c6b</ddb:checksum>
   <ddb:transfer ddb:type="dcterms:URI">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/bitstream/ubsi/952/1/Lisa_Marie_Jacobi.pdf</ddb:transfer>
   <ddb:identifier ddb:type="URL">https://dspace.ub.uni-siegen.de/handle/ubsi/952</ddb:identifier>
   <ddb:rights ddb:kind="free"/>
   <ddb:server>Universitätsbibliothek Siegen</ddb:server>
</xMetaDiss:xMetaDiss>